<?xml version="1.0"?>
<div id="usmle_step">
<h1>Step 3</h1>
<p>Step 3 assesses whether you can apply medical knowledge and understanding of biomedical and clinical science essential for the unsupervised practice of medicine, with emphasis on patient management in ambulatory settings. Step 3 provides a final assessment of physicians assuming independent responsibility for delivering general medical care. A principal organizing dimension for Step 3 design is normal conditions and disease categories. Second and third organizing dimensions are the clinical encounter frame and physician tasks. Step 3 content reflects a data-based model of generalist medical practice in the United States. </p>
<p>The Step 3 2011 content description is available in html and PDF. <a href="step3_content.html">Learn more</a></p>
<p>The Step 3 2010 content description is available in PDF. <a href="2010Step3.pdf">Learn more</a></p>
<p>Step 3 has multiple-choice  test items and  computer-based case simulations.</p>
<p>USMLE orientation materials, including software with practice test items, are available to download from this website. <a href="/Examinations/practice_materials.html">Learn more</a></p>
<p><strong>Recent Step 3 Announcements</strong></p>
<p></p>
<p>Click on the links to the right to view sections of the Step 3 content description in hypertext format. </p>
<p>The purpose of Step 3 is to determine if a physician possesses and can apply the medical knowledge and understanding of clinical science considered essential for the unsupervised practice of medicine, with emphasis on patient management in ambulatory care settings. The inclusion of Step 3 in the USMLE sequence of licensing examinations ensures that attention is devoted to the importance of assessing the knowledge and skills of physicians who are assuming independent responsibility for providing general medical care to patients.</p>
<div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>Step 3 Content Description</h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<h2>Examination Design</h2>&#xD;
	<p>A principal organizing dimension for Step 3 design&#xD;
	  is <em>normal conditions and disease categories</em>. The&#xD;
	  normal conditions section deals with normal growth&#xD;
	  and development, basic concepts, and general&#xD;
	  principles. The remaining sections deal with&#xD;
	  individual diseases/disorders. The <a href="/Examinations/step3/content/disease.html">Problem/Disease List</a> is derived from a model of practice for USMLE. The categories and content coverage in these materials describing Step 3 are subject to change.</p>&#xD;
	<p>	  A second organizing dimension is the <em>clinical&#xD;
	  encounter frame</em>. The concept of frames&#xD;
	  encompasses several elements that are critical to the&#xD;
	  definition of a patient-physician encounter. These&#xD;
	  elements include whether the problem or concern is&#xD;
	  new or ongoing, the urgency of the need for&#xD;
	  intervention relative to the underlying problem, the&#xD;
	  chronology of events, and the degree of familiarity&#xD;
	  with the patient or the patient&#x2019;s history. In addition,&#xD;
	  each encounter between patient and physician occurs&#xD;
	  in a specifically defined location. The clinical&#xD;
	  encounter frames are listed; a more detailed&#xD;
	  description is contained in the <a href="/Examinations/step3/content/clinical_frames.html">Step 3 Clinical Encounter Frames</a>.</p>&#xD;
            <ul><li>&#xD;
                <p>Initial workup. Patient encounters characterized&#xD;
                by new problems among patients seen for the&#xD;
                first time. Tasks emphasized include extensive&#xD;
                data gathering and initial therapeutic&#xD;
                intervention.</p>&#xD;
              </li>&#xD;
              <li>&#xD;
                <p> Continuing care. Patient encounters&#xD;
                  characterized by management of previously&#xD;
                  diagnosed clinical problems among patients.&#xD;
                  Evaluating the severity of the patient&#x2019;s&#xD;
                  problem(s) and prognosis, monitoring therapy,&#xD;
                  and long-term management are emphasized.</p>&#xD;
              </li>&#xD;
              <li>&#xD;
                <p> Urgent intervention. Patient encounters&#xD;
                  characterized by life- and/or organ-threatening&#xD;
                  emergencies usually occurring in emergency&#xD;
                  department or inpatient settings. Tasks&#xD;
                  emphasized include rapid assessment of&#xD;
                  complex presentations and prompt therapeutic&#xD;
                  decision making.</p>&#xD;
              </li>&#xD;
            </ul><p>	  A third organizing dimension for Step 3 design is the	  <em>physician task</em>: (1) applying scientific concepts&#xD;
	  (mechanisms); (2) formulating a diagnosis&#xD;
	  (including history and physical examination,&#xD;
	  laboratory and diagnostic studies, diagnosis,&#xD;
	  prognosis); (3) managing the patient (including&#xD;
	  health maintenance, clinical interventions, clinical&#xD;
	  therapeutics, communication). See <a href="/Examinations/step3/content/physician_tasks .html">Physician Tasks</a> for a more detailed description.</p>&#xD;
      <p>Much of the test material relates to continuing care&#xD;
        encounters as shown in the <a href="/Examinations/step3/content/blueprint.html">Step 3 Blueprint</a>. Hence, the bulk of Step 3 is intended to&#xD;
        challenge you to consider the severity of illness and&#xD;
        to manage ambulatory patients who have previously&#xD;
        diagnosed, frequently occurring chronic illnesses&#xD;
        and behavioral/emotional problems.</p>&#xD;
      <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>Step 3 Content Description</h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<h2>Examination Format</h2>&#xD;
	<p>Step 3 consists of multiple-choice items and computer-based case simulations, distributed according to the content blueprint. The examination material is prepared by examination committees broadly representing the medical profession. The committees comprise recognized experts in their fields, including both academic and non-academic practitioners, as well as members of state medical licensing boards.</p>&#xD;
	<p>Step 3 is a two-day examination. You must complete each day of testing within 8 hours. The first day of testing includes 336 multiple-choice items divided into 7 blocks of 48 items each. There will be 60 minutes of time allowed for completion of each block of test items. There is a maximum of 7 hours of testing on the first day. There is also a minimum of 45 minutes of break time and a 15-minute optional tutorial. Note that the amount of time available for breaks may be increased by finishing a block of test items or the optional tutorial before the allotted time expires. </p>&#xD;
	<p>The second day of testing includes 144 multiple-choice items, divided into 4 blocks of 36 items. These blocks will take 45 minutes. The total time allotted for these blocks is 3 hours. The second day also includes a <em>Primum&#xAE; Tutorial</em> and instructions for which approximately 15 minutes are allowed. This is followed by 9 case simulations, for which 4 hours are allotted.  To download the tutorial and practice materials for Primum, click on <a href="/Examinations/practice_materials.html">USMLE Practice and Orientation Materials</a>. A minimum of 45 minutes is available for break time. There is an optional survey at the end of the second day, which can be completed if time allows. The timing and structure of the Step 3 testing days may change without notice; please refer to the <a href="../../../index.html">USMLE website</a> for the most up-to-date information.</p>&#xD;
	<h2>Multiple-choice items</h2>&#xD;
	<p>One-best-choice formats are used. Items may stand alone or may be sequenced together as a case or set of 2 to 3 items. It will be useful to study the descriptions in <a href="../step3_test.html">Test Item Formats</a> and to complete the <a href="../../../Orientation/2010/Menu.html">Tutorial and Sample Tests</a>. Test items present detailed clinical situations, usually from the patient's perspective. The presentation may be supplemented by one or more pictorials, or audio or video. Assessing the patient's situation in the context of his or her environment or family is an important element of many Step 3 questions.</p>&#xD;
	<p>As is done for the actual examination, the sample test items are arranged in blocks that are organized by one of the two <a href="clinical_settings.html">Clinical Settings</a>. During the time allotted to complete the test items in a block, examinees may answer the items in any order, review responses, and change answers. After exiting a block, no further review of items or changing of answers within that block is possible. Policies regarding review of test questions may be changed without notice. The most current policies are provided at the <a href="../../../index.html">USMLE homepage </a>. The computer interface includes, among other features, clickable icons for marking questions to be reviewed, automated review of marked and incomplete items, and a clock indicating the time remaining in the block and in the examination. Practice with the <a href="http://www.usmle.org/examinations/practice_materials.html">sample multiple-choice items</a> will provide examinees with a realistic understanding of the computer interface and timing of the examination.</p>&#xD;
	<p>A table of normal Laboratory Values for frequently ordered laboratory tests, including Standard International conversions, is available in each test item block as a button that retrieves the table for easy viewing.</p>&#xD;
	<h2>Primum Computer-based Case Simulations (CCS)</h2>&#xD;
	<p>You will manage one case at a time. Free-text entry of patient orders is the primary means for interacting with the format. Buttons and check boxes are used for advancing the clock, changing the patient's location, reviewing previously displayed information, and obtaining updates on the patient.</p>&#xD;
	<p>At the beginning of each case, you will see the clinical setting, simulated case time, and introductory patient information. Photographs and sounds will not be provided. Normal or reference laboratory values will be provided with each report; some tests will be accompanied by a clinical interpretation. To  manage patients using the Primum CCS software, it is essential that you  complete the <em>Primum</em> <a href="../../practice_materials.html">tutorial and  sample cases</a> provided. A brief description of the interface is provided in the <em>Primum </em><em>Tutorial</em>. </p>&#xD;
<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>Step 3 Content Description</h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<h2>Clinical Context of Step 3</h2>&#xD;
	<p>Step 3 is the final examination in the USMLE sequence leading to a license to practice medicine without supervision. The test items and cases reflect the clinical situations that a general, as-yet undifferentiated, physician might encounter within the context of a specific setting.</p> &#xD;
	<p>The expected outcome of the USMLE process is a general unrestricted license to practice medicine without supervision. Although you may already have begun specialist training, for this examination you are expected to assume the role of a general, as yet undifferentiated, physician. You are a member of an independent group practice affiliated with a number of managed care organizations. Your office has regularly scheduled hours. You can admit patients to a 400-bed regional hospital, which provides care for both the urban and the outlying rural communities. The hospital provides standard diagnostic, radiologic, and therapeutic options, including ICUs and cardiothoracic surgery. There is a labor and delivery suite. A fully equipped emergency department adjoins the hospital, and medical evacuation helicopter service is available for emergency transfer to a regional trauma center. You do not have specialty-oriented hospital privileges, but you may request any specialty consultation. The laboratory values, included as an on-screen reference in the sample test materials, are the normal ranges for this hospital. </p>&#xD;
	<p>Step 3 patients are intended to reflect the diversity of health care populations with respect to age, sex, cultural group, and occupation. The patient population mix is intended to be representative of data collected from various national databases that study health care in the United States. </p>&#xD;
	<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>Step 3 Content Description</h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<h2>Step 3 Clinical Settings</h2>&#xD;
	<p>The items in each test are usually&#xD;
	  arranged by the setting in which the encounter first&#xD;
	  occurs. There are two settings. To&#xD;
	  help orient you, each setting is described at the&#xD;
	  beginning of the corresponding test block.</p>&#xD;
	<h2>Setting I: Office/Health Center </h2>&#xD;
	<p>You see patients in two locations: your office suite, which is adjacent to a hospital, and at a community-based health center. Your office practice is in a primary care generalist group. Patients are seen for routine and urgent care at the office and health center. Most of the patients you see are from your own practice, although occasionally you will see a patient cared for by one of your associates and reference may be made to the patient's medical records. Known patients may be managed by telephone, and you may have to respond to questions about information appearing in the public media, which will require interpretation of the medical literature. The laboratory and radiology departments have a full range of services available. </p>&#xD;
	<h2>Setting II: Emergency Department and Inpatient Facilities </h2>&#xD;
	<p>You encounter patients in the emergency department and inpatient facilities, including the hospital, the adjacent nursing home/extended-care facility, and detoxification unit. Most patients in the emergency department are new to you and are seeking urgent care, but occasionally you arrange to meet there with a known patient who has telephoned you. You have general admitting privileges to the hospital, including to the children's and women's services. On occasion you see patients in the critical care unit. Postoperative patients are usually seen in their rooms unless the recovery room is specified. You may also be called to see patients in the psychiatric unit. There is a short-stay unit where you may see patients undergoing same-day operations or being held for observation. Also available to you is a full range of social services, including rape crisis intervention, family support, and security assistance backed up by local police. </p>&#xD;
	<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>Step 3 Content Description</h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<h2>Step 3 Clinical Encounter Frames</h2>&#xD;
	<br/><br/><p>The content description that follows is not intended as a study guide, but rather is a model of the range of challenges that will be met in the actual practice of medicine. Successful completion of at least one year of postgraduate training in a program accredited by the Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education or the American Osteopathic Association should be helpful preparation for Step 3.</p>&#xD;
	<table><colgroup><col span="1" valign="top"/><col class="alternative" valign="top"/><col class="2ndalternative" valign="top"/></colgroup><tr><th bgcolor="#CCCCCC">INITIAL WORKUP </th>&#xD;
				<th bgcolor="#E7E7E7">CONTINUING CARE</th>&#xD;
				<th>URGENT INTERVENTION </th>&#xD;
			</tr><tr><th bgcolor="#CCCCCC">1</th>&#xD;
				<th bgcolor="#E7E7E7">2</th>&#xD;
				<th>3</th>&#xD;
			</tr><tr><td bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Patient encounters characterized by initial assessment and management of clinical problems among patients seen principally in <strong>ambulatory settings for the first time</strong>. These encounters may also include new problems arising in patients for whom a history is available. </td>&#xD;
				<td bgcolor="#E7E7E7">Patient encounters characterized by continuing management of previously diagnosed clinical problems among patients known to the physician and seen <strong>principally in ambulatory settings</strong>. Encounters focused on health maintenance are located in this frame. <br/><br/>Also included are patient encounters characterized by acute exacerbations or complications, principally of chronic, progressive conditions among patients known to the physician. These encounters may occur in <strong>inpatient settings</strong>. </td>&#xD;
				<td>Patient encounters characterized by prompt assessment and management of life-threatening and organ- threatening emergencies,<strong> usually occurring in emergency department settings</strong>.<br/><br/>Occasionally, these encounters may occur in the context of a hospitalized patient.</td>&#xD;
			</tr><tr><td bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Clinical problems include ill-defined signs and symptoms; behavioral-emotional; acute limited; initial manifestation and presentation of chronic illness. </td>&#xD;
				<td bgcolor="#E7E7E7">Clinical problems include frequently occurring chronic diseases and behavioral-emotional problems. Periodic health evaluations of established patients are included here.</td>&#xD;
				<td>Clinical problems include severe life-threatening and organ-threatening conditions and exacerbations of chronic illness.</td>&#xD;
			</tr><tr><td bgcolor="#CCCCCC">Physician tasks emphasized include data gathering and initial clinical intervention. Assessment of patients may lead to urgent intervention. </td>&#xD;
				<td bgcolor="#E7E7E7">Physician tasks emphasized include recognition of new problems in an existing condition, assessment of severity, establishing prognosis, monitoring therapy, and long-term management. </td>&#xD;
				<td>Physician tasks emphasized include rapid assessment of complex presentations, assessment of patients' deteriorating condition, and prompt decision making. </td>&#xD;
			</tr></table><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>Step 3 Content Description</h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<h2>Step 3 Physician Tasks</h2>&#xD;
	<h3>Applying Scientific Concepts </h3>&#xD;
	<p class="alpha">Objectives focus on identifying the underlying processes or pathways responsible for a given condition, &#xD;
	  recognizing associated disease conditions and complications, and recognizing and evaluating clinical &#xD;
	  findings or diagnostic studies to identify the underlying factors (eg, anatomic structure).</p>&#xD;
	<h3>Formulating a Diagnosis</h3>&#xD;
	<p>	  <em>History and Physical Examination</em> objectives focus on interpreting the patient&#x2019;s history, knowing &#xD;
  pertinent factors in the patient&#x2019;s history, interpreting the history in terms of risk factors for the patient, &#xD;
	  recognizing and interpreting pertinent physical findings, and knowing required techniques in the &#xD;
	  physical examination.</p>&#xD;
	<p><em>Laboratory and Diagnostic Studies</em> objectives focus on selecting the appropriate routine, initial, &#xD;
	  invasive, special, or follow-up studies; interpreting the results of laboratory or diagnostic tests; &#xD;
	  knowing the value of and indications for screening tests; and predicting the most likely test result.</p>&#xD;
	<p><em>Diagnosis </em>objectives focus on selecting the most likely diagnosis in light of history, physical, or &#xD;
	  diagnostic test findings. Includes interpreting pictorial material and establishing a diagnosis.</p>&#xD;
	<p><em>Prognosis</em> objectives focus on interpreting the vignette, evaluating the severity of the patient&#x2019;s &#xD;
	  condition, and making judgment on the current status or prognosis of the patient as to the need for &#xD;
	  further action.</p>&#xD;
	<h3>Managing the Patient	  </h3>&#xD;
	<p><em>Health Maintenance</em> objectives focus on identifying risk factors, knowing incidence within patient &#xD;
	  groups at risk, knowing preliminary steps to ensure effectiveness of intended therapy, and selecting &#xD;
	  appropriate preventive therapeutic agents or techniques.</p>&#xD;
	<p>	  <em>Clinical Intervention</em> objectives focus on knowing priorities in emergency management, knowing &#xD;
	  present and long-term management of selected conditions, and knowing appropriate surgical treatment, &#xD;
	  including pre- and post-surgical events. They also include knowing pre- and post-procedural &#xD;
	  management and the appropriate follow-up schedule or monitoring approach.</p>&#xD;
	<p>	  <em>Clinical Therapeutics</em> objectives focus on selecting the appropriate pharmacotherapy, recognizing &#xD;
	  actions of drugs as applied to patient management, and knowing the importance of educating patients &#xD;
	  about effects of drugs and drug-drug interactions.</p>&#xD;
	<p>	  <em>Legal/ethical and health care systems</em> objectives focus on issues such as patient autonomy, physician/patient relationships, use of unorthodox or experimental therapies, end-of-life considerations, treatment of minors, and physician error versus negligence. </p>&#xD;
<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>Step 3 Content Description</h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<h2>Step 3 Evaluative Objectives	</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p>The Step 3 Evaluative Objectives are categorized according to the physician tasks and they serve to guide writing&#xD;
	  and classification of test items. They can be read as more detailed descriptions of the kinds of issues that will be&#xD;
	  posed to physicians taking Step 3.</p>&#xD;
	<h2>Applying Scientific Concepts </h2>&#xD;
	<ul><li>&#xD;
		    <p>Identifies the cause/causal agent or predisposing factor(s); or, given an effect, what is the cause.</p>&#xD;
		  </li>&#xD;
		  <li>&#xD;
	        <p>Identifies the underlying processes/pathways that account for, or contribute to, the expression or resolution&#xD;
	        of a given condition.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
	      <li>&#xD;
	        <p>Recognizes or evaluates given clinical or physical findings to identify the underlying anatomic structure or&#xD;
	        physical location.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
        <li>&#xD;
          <p>Interprets results of clinical studies.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
      </ul><h2>Obtaining History and Performing Physical Examination </h2>&#xD;
	<ul><li>&#xD;
		    <p>Knows signs/symptoms of selected disorders.</p>&#xD;
		  </li>&#xD;
          <li>&#xD;
            <p>Knows individual&#x2019;s risk factors for development of condition leading to encounter. Given current symptoms&#xD;
              in presented history, identifies pertinent factor(s) in history.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
	      <li>&#xD;
	        <p>Predicts the most likely additional physical finding; selects either the finding itself, or the appropriate&#xD;
	          examination technique that would result in the finding.</p>&#xD;
	      </li>&#xD;
	      <li>&#xD;
	        <p>Given a specific problem, knows what to ask in obtaining pertinent additional history. </p>&#xD;
	      </li>&#xD;
	</ul><h2>Using Laboratory and Diagnostic Studies</h2>&#xD;
	  <ul><li>&#xD;
	      <p>Selects appropriate routine or initial laboratory or diagnostic studies, or study needed to ensure<br/>&#xD;
	        effectiveness of intended therapy, or study most likely to establish/confirm the diagnosis.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
        <li>&#xD;
          <p>Interprets the clinical impact of laboratory or diagnostic test findings.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
	    <li>	      &#xD;
	      <p>Predicts the most likely laboratory or diagnostic test result.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
      </ul><h2>	        Formulating the Most Likely Diagnosis</h2>&#xD;
	  <ul><li>&#xD;
	      <p>Selects the most likely diagnosis or knows the most likely presumptive or preliminary diagnosis.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
      </ul><h2> Evaluating the Severity of Patient Problems (Prognosis)</h2>&#xD;
	  <ul><li>&#xD;
	      <p>Evaluates severity of patient condition and identifies indications for consultation or diagnostic assessment.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li>&#xD;
	      <p>Assesses severity of patient condition and makes judgment as to current status, prognosis, or need for&#xD;
	        further action.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li>&#xD;
	      <p>Recognizes factors in the history, or physical or laboratory study findings (given symptoms), that affect&#xD;
	        patient prognosis or outcome, or determine therapy.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li>	      &#xD;
	      <p>Interprets laboratory or diagnostic study results and identifies current status of patient.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
        <li>&#xD;
          <p>Recognizes associated disease conditions, including complications, or indicators for potential disease complications, of a given disease.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
	    <li>&#xD;
	      <p>Recognizes characteristics of disease relating to natural history or course of disease, including progression, severity, duration, and transmission of disease.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li>&#xD;
	      <p>Knows appropriate counseling of patient or family regarding current and future problems, including risk factors related to present encounter.   </p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	  </ul><h2>	        Management of Health Maintenance and Disease Prevention</h2>&#xD;
	  <ul><li>&#xD;
	      <p>Knows risk factors for conditions amenable to prevention or detection in an asymptomatic patient, or knows&#xD;
	        the potential condition itself.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
	    <li>&#xD;
	      <p>Knows pertinent incidence statistics and identifies patient groups at risk; knows incidence of<br/>&#xD;
	        symptomless/dangerous disorders among various groups.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
	    <li>&#xD;
	      <p>Knows common screening tests for conditions amenable to prevention or detection in an asymptomatic&#xD;
	        patient or population.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
	    <li>&#xD;
	      <p>Selects appropriate preventive, therapeutic agent/technique. Knows timing of vaccinations. </p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
      </ul><h2>Clinical Interventions</h2>&#xD;
	  <ul><li class="style1">	      &#xD;
	      <p>Evaluates severity of patient condition in terms of need for referral for surgical treatments/procedures&#xD;
	        versus other nonsurgical options.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
        <li class="style1">          &#xD;
          <p>Knows immediate management or priority in management, specifically in emergency or acute cases.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
	    <li class="style1">	      &#xD;
	      <p>Knows most appropriate management of selected conditions.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li class="style1">	      &#xD;
	      <p>Knows appropriate long-term treatment or management goals.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li class="style1">	      &#xD;
	      <p>Knows appropriate surgical management among surgical options.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li class="style1">	      &#xD;
	      <p>Knows pre/post surgical or procedural management.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li class="style1">	      &#xD;
	      <p>Knows indications for admission to the hospital or to another appropriate setting.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li class="style1">	      &#xD;
	      <p>Knows most appropriate follow-up monitoring approach regarding the management plan.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li class="style1">	      &#xD;
	      <p>Knows most appropriate discharge planning.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li class="style1">	      &#xD;
	      <p>Knows components of rehabilitation program.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li class="style1">	      &#xD;
	      <p>Educates patient or family regarding self-care.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li class="style1">	      &#xD;
	      <p>Knows relevant roles of allied health personnel.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li>	      &#xD;
	      <p><span class="style1">Knows appropriate use and procedures regarding hospice care.</span></p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
      </ul><h2>Clinical Therapeutics</h2>&#xD;
	  <ul><li>&#xD;
	      <p> Selects most appropriate pharmacotherapy.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
        <li>&#xD;
          <p> Assesses patient adherence with treatment regimen, recognizes techniques to increase adherence or&#xD;
            understanding of the disease state, and knows how adherence may be affected by providing instructions&#xD;
            with therapy.</p>&#xD;
        </li>&#xD;
	    <li>&#xD;
	      <p> Recognizes factors that alter drug requirements for a patient.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li>&#xD;
	      <p>Knows adverse effects of various drugs, or recognizes signs and symptoms of drug (and drug-drug)&#xD;
	        interactions resulting from polypharmacy in the therapeutic regimen and knows steps to prevent&#xD;
	        polypharmacy.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li>&#xD;
	      <p>Knows contraindications of various medications.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
	    <li>&#xD;
	      <p>Modifies therapeutic regimen within the context of continuing care.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
      </ul><h2>        Communication</h2>&#xD;
	  <ul><li>&#xD;
	      <p>Recognizes physician&#x2019;s best choice of words in eliciting history or further description of the patient's&#xD;
	        problem; knows statements that facilitate communication with the patient.</p>&#xD;
	    </li>&#xD;
      </ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>Step 3 Content Description</h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<p>The following table shows how frames and tasks intersect to create the Step 3 blueprint that specifies the broad content allocations for constructing Step 3. Estimates of approximate percentages are provided for the marginal totals.</p>&#xD;
	<h2>Step 3 Blueprint</h2>&#xD;
	<img src="../../../img/blueprint.gif" alt="Step 3 Blueprint" width="511" height="378"/><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>Step 3 Content Description</h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<h2>Step 3 Problem/Disease List </h2>&#xD;
	<p>The design of the Step 3 Content Outline has been influenced by the review of empirical data drawn from several sources, including, for example, the National Ambulatory Medical Care Survey and the National Hospital Discharge Survey. The diseases noted in the outline do <em>not</em> represent an all-inclusive registry of disorders about which questions may be asked. Questions are generally, <em>but not exclusively</em>, focused on the listed disorders. In addition, not all listed topics are included on each examination.</p>&#xD;
	<h2>General Principles</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Normal Development</strong><br/><em>Infancy/Childhood</em> (eg, normal growth and development)<br/><em>Adolescence</em> (eg, sexuality, physical changes of puberty)<br/><em>Adult</em> (eg, normal physical findings and lifestyle issues)<br/><em>Senescence</em> (eg, normal physical and mental changes of aging)</p>&#xD;
	<p>	  <strong>Medical Ethics and Jurisprudence</strong><br/><em>Consent and Informed Consent to Treatment</em> (eg, full disclosure, advance directives/health care proxy, permission to treat, competency, autonomy)<br/><em>Physician/Patient Relationship</em> (eg, truth-telling, confidentiality, privacy, adult maltreatment [including elder abuse], child maltreatment [child abuse])<br/><em>Death and Dying</em> (eg, diagnosing death, organ donation, euthanasia/physician-assisted suicide, palliative care)</p>&#xD;
	<p>	  <strong>Applied Biostatistics and Clinical Epidemiology</strong><br/><em>Understanding Statistical Concepts</em> (eg, understanding statistical concepts, calculations of one thing/multiple things, mixed calculations/interpretations)<br/><em>Interpretation of the Medical Literature</em> (eg, interpretation of a study statement, reading a table or graph, evaluation of the validity of the author's conclusion, identification of the study flaw, design of a study)</p>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Systems-Based Care and Patient Safety</strong><br/><em>Systems-Based Practice and Quality Improvement</em> (eg, microsystems and teams including hand-offs, standardization of processes, reducing deviance)<br/><em>Patient Safety, Medical Errors and Near Misses</em> (eg, sentinel events, problem identification, root cause analysis)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>Disorders of the Nervous System and Special Senses</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Degenerative/Developmental Disorders</strong> (eg, Alzheimer disease, Parkinson disease, multiple sclerosis, cerebral&#xD;
	  palsy)<br/><strong>Neuromuscular/Degenerative Disorders </strong> (eg, paraplegia, myasthenia&#xD;
	  gravis, spinal stenosis, neuritis)<br/><strong>Cerebrovascular Diseases</strong> (eg, intracranial hemorrhage, transient cerebral ischemias, stroke, vascular dementia&#xD;
	  [multi-infarct dementia])<br/><strong>Peripheral Nerve Diseases</strong> (eg, carpal tunnel syndrome, nerve compression, neuropathy)<br/><strong>Headache and Movement Disorders</strong> (eg, seizure disorder, trigeminal neuralgia, Bell palsy, torticollis)<br/><strong>Sleep Disorders</strong> (eg, night terrors and sleepwalking, cataplexy and narcolepsy)<br/><strong>Neoplasms</strong> (eg, meningioma, metastatic lesions)<br/><strong>Infectious Diseases</strong> (eg, tetanus, Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, meningitis, encephalitis)<br/><strong>Trauma and Toxic Effects</strong> (eg, intracranial injury, brain death, coma, concussion)<br/><strong>Disorders of the Eye</strong> (eg, glaucoma, retinal detachment, cataract, corneal abrasion)<br/><strong>Disorders of the Ear</strong> (eg, perforation of tympanic membrane, acoustic neuroma, hearing loss, vertigo)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>	  Disorders of the Respiratory System</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p>	  <strong>Obstructive Airways Disease</strong> (eg, cystic fibrosis, chronic bronchitis, emphysema, asthma)<br/><strong>Pneumoconiosis/Fibrosing or Restrictive Pulmonary Disorders</strong> (eg, sarcoidosis, asbestosis, pneumoconiosis,&#xD;
	  pulmonary fibrosis)<br/><strong>Respiratory Failure &amp; Pulmonary Vascular Disease</strong> (eg, pulmonary hypertension, respiratory distress syndrome, atelectasis, pulmonary embolism)<br/><strong>Upper Respiratory Conditions</strong> (eg, sinusitis, peritonsillar abscess, otitis, streptococcal throat infection)<br/><strong>Neoplasms</strong> (eg, mesothelioma, paraneoplastic syndrome)<br/><strong>Lung Infections</strong> (eg, pulmonary tuberculosis, pneumonia, influenza, respiratory syncytial virus)<br/><strong>Trauma and Toxic Effects</strong> (eg, pleurisy, pleural effusion, pneumothorax, drowning and nonfatal submersion)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>Cardiovascular Disorders</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Hypertensive Disease</strong> (eg, hypertension, elevated blood pressure)<br/><strong>Hypotension</strong> (eg, orthostatic hypotension, hypotensive emergency)<br/><strong>Ischemic Heart Disease and Atherosclerosis</strong> (eg, myocardial infarction, ischemic heart disease, angina pectoris, hyperlipidemia, arteriosclerosis)<br/><strong>Congestive Heart Failure</strong> (eg, congestive heart failure, left heart failure)<br/><strong>Dysrhythmias</strong> (eg, atrioventricular block, paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardia, fibrillation and flutter, cardiac arrest)<br/><strong>Disorders of the Great Vessels</strong> (eg, atherosclerosis of aorta, dissecting aneurysm, aortic aneurysm)<br/><strong>Valvular Heart Disease</strong> (eg, rheumatic heart disease,  endocarditis, valve disorders, functional murmurs)<br/><strong>Peripheral Arterial Vascular Diseases</strong> (eg, Raynaud syndrome, intermittent claudication, arterial embolism/thrombosis)<br/><strong>Diseases of Veins</strong> (eg, phlebitis/thrombophlebitis, deep venous thrombosis, varicose veins, venous insufficiency)<br/><strong>Congenital Disease</strong> (eg, ventricular/atrial septal defect, patent ductus arteriosus, coarctation of aorta, tetralogy of Fallot)<br/><strong>Diseases of Myocardium</strong> (eg, hypertensive cardiomegaly, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, myocarditis)<br/><strong>Diseases of Pericardium</strong> (eg, pericarditis, pericardial tamponade)<br/><strong>Trauma and Toxic Effects</strong> (eg, cardiovascular injury, fat embolism)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>Nutritional and Digestive System Disorders</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Mouth, Salivary Glands, and Esophagus</strong> (eg, malignant neoplasm of mouth/salivary<br/>&#xD;
	  glands/esophagus, esophageal varices, esophagitis/esophageal reflux, diaphragmatic hernia)<br/><strong>Stomach</strong> (eg, neoplasm of stomach, gastric ulcer problems, peptic ulcer problems, gastritis and duodenitis)<br/><strong>Small Intestine/Colon and Rectum</strong> (eg, inflammatory bowel disease, diverticula, anal fissure or fistula, celiac disease)<br/><strong>Gallbladder and Bile Duct</strong> (eg, calculus of gallbladder, cholangitis, obstruction of common bile duct and biliary atresia)<br/><strong>Liver</strong> (eg, acute hepatic failure, cirrhosis, ascites, fatty liver disease)<br/><strong>Pancreas</strong> (eg, neoplasm of pancreas or Islets of Langerhans, pancreatitis, cyst and pseudocyst of pancreas)<br/><strong>Nutritional Disorders </strong> (eg, obesity, malnutrition and malabsorption)<br/><strong>Infections</strong> (eg, gastroenteritis, coxsackievirus, candidiasis of mouth [thrush], hepatitis A/B/C, <em>Helicobacter pylori</em>)<br/><strong>Trauma and Toxic Effects</strong> (eg, food poisoning, hernia of abdominal cavity, ventral hernia)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>	  Behavioral/Emotional Disorders</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Psychotic Disorders</strong> (eg, schizophrenia, paranoid state, psychotic disorder)<br/><strong>Anxiety Disorders</strong> (eg, panic disorder [panic attacks], phobic disorders, obsessive-compulsive disorders, posttraumatic stress disorder)<br/><strong>Mood Disorders</strong> (eg, dysthymic disorder, depressive disorders, bipolar disorders, postpartum depression)<br/><strong>Somatoform Disorders</strong> (eg, somatization disorder, malingering, conversion disorder, hypochondriasis [including body dysmorphic disorder])<br/><strong>Eating Disorders and Other Impulse Control Disorders</strong> (eg,  bulimia, disorders of impulse control [gambling, shoplifting], binge eating disorder)<br/><strong>Disorders Originating in Infancy/Childhood/Adolescence</strong> (eg, oppositional defiant disorder, attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder, developmental speech or language disorder, autistic disorder)<br/><strong>Personality Disorders</strong> (eg, antisocial personality disorder, dependent personality disorder, paranoid personality disorder, schizoid personality disorder)<br/><strong>Psychosocial Problems</strong> (eg, psychosexual dysfunction, bereavement)<br/><strong>Substance Use Disorders</strong> (eg, alcohol abuse and dependence, alcohol withdrawal syndrome, cocaine/opiates/sedatives/hypnotics abuse and dependence)<br/><strong>Toxic Effects</strong> (eg, poisoning by psychotropic agents, including antidepressants)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>Disorders of the Musculoskeletal System</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Degenerative/Metabolic Disorders</strong> (eg, gout, osteoarthritis, avascular necrosis of bone, disc displacement)<br/><strong>Inflammatory/Immunologic Disorders</strong> (eg, ankylosis/spondylopathy, rheumatoid arthritis,<br/>&#xD;
	  synovitis/tenosynovitis, myalgia and myositis)<br/><strong>Hereditary Developmental Disorders</strong> (eg, genu valgum or varum, congenital dislocation of hip, scoliosis,&#xD;
	  varus/valgus deformities of feet)<br/><strong>Neoplasms </strong>(eg, secondary malignant neoplasm of bone and bone marrow, osteosarcoma)<br/><strong>Infections</strong> (eg, infective arthritis, infective myositis, Lyme disease, osteomyelitis)<br/><strong>Traumatic Injuries</strong> (eg, tears, fractures, dislocations, contusions)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>Disorders of the Skin/Subcutaneous Tissue</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Skin Eruptions</strong> (eg, contact dermatitis, erythema multiforme, psoriasis, decubitus ulcer)<br/><strong>Disorders of Nails/Hair/Sweat Glands</strong> (eg, ingrowing nail, seborrhea capitis/folliculitis/sycosis, hirsutism,&#xD;
	  hyperhidrosis)<br/><strong>Lumps/Tumors of the Skin</strong> (eg, malignant melanoma of skin/lip, keratoderma, sebaceous cyst,<br/>&#xD;
	  neurofibromatosis)<br/><strong>Infections</strong> (eg, tinea infections, cellulitis and abscess, erythema infectiosum, molluscum contagiosum)<br/><strong>Trauma and Toxic Effects</strong> (eg, wounds or burns affecting the skin or subcutaneous tissue, keloid scar, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, frostbite)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>	  Disorders of the Endocrine System</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Thyroid Disorders</strong> (eg, malignant neoplasm of thyroid gland, thyrotoxicosis, hypothyroidism, thyroiditis)<br/><strong>Diabetes Mellitus</strong> (eg, ketoacidosis, renal manifestations, neurologic manifestations, hypoglycemic shock)<br/><strong>Adrenal Disorders</strong> (eg, neuroblastoma, hyperaldosteronism, congenital adrenal hyperplasia, corticoadrenal&#xD;
	  insufficiency [Addison disease])<br/><strong>Parathyroid/Pituitary Disorders</strong> (eg, hyperparathyroidism, hypoparathyroidism, prolactinoma,<br/>&#xD;
	  pheochromocytoma)<br/><strong>Trauma and Toxic Effects</strong> (eg, heat syncope, heat stroke and sun stroke, heat exhaustion)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>Renal and Urinary Disorders</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Lower Urinary Tract</strong> (eg, neurogenic bladder, enuresis/incontinence of urine, urinary obstruction, cystitis)<br/><strong>Upper Urinary Tract</strong> (eg, glomerulonephritis, renal failure/insufficiency, polycystic kidney disease, calculus of&#xD;
	  kidney/ureter/urinary tract)<br/><strong>Fluid, Electrolyte, and Acid-Base Disorders </strong>(eg, dehydration, hypovolemia, electrolyte imbalances, metabolic&#xD;
	  disorders)<br/><strong>Infections</strong> (eg, pyelonephritis, urethritis, urinary tract infection)<br/><strong>Trauma and Toxic Effects</strong> (eg, extravasation of urine)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>Diseases/Disorders of the Female Reproductive System</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Breast</strong> (eg, fibrocystic/solitary cyst of breast, hypertrophy of breast, disorders of lactation, mastitis)<br/><strong>Uterus</strong> (eg, leiomyoma of uterus, postcoital bleeding, endometriosis of uterus, uterine prolapse)<br/><strong>Ovary, Fallopian Tube, &amp; Broad Ligament</strong> (eg, ovarian or fallopian tube torsion, ovarian cyst, ovarian failure,&#xD;
	  benign neoplasm of ovary)<br/><strong>Cervix</strong> (eg, cervix uteri, cervicitis and endocervicitis, dysplasia of cervix [uteri], abnormal Pap smear of cervix)<br/><strong>Vagina/Vulva</strong> (eg, vaginitis and vulvovaginitis, prolapse of vaginal walls, imperforate hymen, vaginismus)<br/><strong>Menstrual Disorders</strong> (eg, dysmenorrhea, premenstrual tension syndrome, irregular menstrual cycle, ovulation&#xD;
	  bleeding)<br/><strong>Menopause</strong> (eg, postmenopausal hormone replacement therapy, premenopausal menorrhagia, postmenopausal bleeding, postmenopausal atrophic vaginitis)<br/><strong>Pelvic Relaxation and Urinary Disorders </strong> (eg, stress incontinence, uterine prolapse, prolapse of vaginal walls, cystocele/rectocele)<br/><strong>Female Fertility/Infertility</strong> (eg, contraception, pre-pregnancy counseling, dyspareunia, female infertility)<br/><strong>Neoplasms</strong> (eg, malignant neoplasm of breast, uterus, ovary, vagina/vulva; cervical cancer)<br/><strong>Infections</strong> (eg, human papillomavirus, sexually transmitted diseases, pelvic inflammatory disease, salpingitis and&#xD;
	  oophoritis)<br/><strong>Trauma and Toxic Effects</strong> (eg, injuries, wounds, toxic effects, or burns affecting the female reproductive system)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>Pregnancy/Labor and Delivery/Fetus and Newborn</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Pregnancy: Complicated</strong> (eg, gestational diabetes, ectopic/tubal pregnancy, preeclampsia or eclampsia, cervical&#xD;
	  incompetence)<br/><strong>Pregnancy: Uncomplicated</strong> (eg, supervision of normal pregnancy, examination of liveborn before admission to&#xD;
	  hospital)<br/><strong>Labor, Delivery, &amp; Postpartum (including placenta abnormalities)</strong> (eg, premature rupture of membranes,&#xD;
	  infections complicating childbirth, cesarean delivery, immediate postpartum hemorrhage)<br/><strong>Fetus &amp; Newborn</strong> (eg, congenital anomalies, Down syndrome, neonatal hypoglycemia, feeding problems in&#xD;
	  newborn [breast-feeding])<br/><strong>Perinatal Infections</strong> (eg, congenital cytomegalovirus infection, neonatal conjunctivitis and dacryocystitis, neonatal sepsis,&#xD;
	  herpes simplex virus)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>	  Disorders of Blood</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Splenic Disorders</strong> (eg, traumatic and nontraumatic diseases of spleen)<br/><strong>Anemias and Cytopenias</strong> (eg, iron deficiency anemia, hereditary spherocytosis, hemoglobinopathies, thrombocytopenic purpura and ITP)<br/><strong>Bleeding Disorders</strong> (eg, coagulation defects, congenital factor VIII disorder/hemophilia, von Willebrand disease,&#xD;
	  disseminated intravascular coagulation)<br/><strong>Reactions to Blood Components</strong> (eg, transfusion reaction, ABO incompatibility reaction, Rh incompatibility&#xD;
	  reaction)<br/><strong>Malignant Neoplasias</strong> (eg, Hodgkin disease, lymphomas, multiple myeloma, leukemia)<br/><strong>Infections</strong> (eg, infectious mononucleosis, cat-scratch disease, septicemia, lymphadenitis)<br/><strong>Toxic Effects</strong> (eg, heparin-induced thrombocytopenia)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>Disorders of the Male Reproductive System</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Male Reproductive System</strong> (eg, neoplasm of male breast/prostate/testes, prostatitis, torsion of testes, orchitis/epididymitis)<br/><strong>Infections</strong> (eg, human papillomavirus, sexually transmitted diseases)<br/><strong>Trauma and Toxic Effects</strong> (eg, injuries, wounds, toxic effects, or burns affecting the male reproductive system)</p>&#xD;
	<hr/><h2>Disorders of the Immune System</h2>&#xD;
	<h2>&#xA0;</h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Immune Deficiency Disorders</strong> (eg, hypogammaglobulinemia, IgA deficiency)<br/><strong>HIV</strong> (eg, AIDS, AIDS-related complex, pneumocystosis, Kaposi sarcoma)<br/><strong>Vascular/Arterial Disorders</strong> (eg, Wegener granulomatosis, arteritis)<br/><strong>MSK/Connective Tissue Disorders</strong> (eg, dermatomyositis, polymyositis, polymyalgia rheumatica, systemic lupus&#xD;
	  erythematosus)<br/><strong>Vaccinations/Chemotherapy</strong> (eg, routine and nonroutine, including travel vaccinations, prophylactic and maintenance chemotherapy)<br/><strong>Anaphylaxis/Immunologic reactions</strong> (eg, anaphylaxis, reactions to venomous bites, desensitization to allergens)<br/><strong>Infections</strong> (eg, scarlet fever, toxic shock syndrome, Rocky Mountain spotted fever, retrovirus)</p>&#xD;
<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div>
</div>
