<?xml version="1.0"?>
<div id="usmle_step">
<h1>Step 2</h1>
<p>Step 2 assesses whether you can apply medical knowledge, skills, and understanding of clinical science essential for the provision of patient care under supervision and includes emphasis on health promotion and disease prevention. Step 2 ensures that due attention is devoted to principles of clinical sciences and basic patient-centered skills that provide the foundation for the safe and competent practice of medicine.    </p>
<p> Step 2 CK   is constructed according to an integrated content outline that organizes clinical science material along two dimensions: physician task and disease category.	<a href="step2ck.html" target="_self">Learn more</a></p>
<p>Step 2 CS uses standardized patients, i.e., people trained to portray real patients.  The cases cover common and important situations that a physician is likely to encounter in clinics, doctors&#8217; offices, emergency departments, and hospital settings in the United States. <a href="step2cs.html" target="_self" class="real"> Learn more</a></p>
<p>USMLE  orientation materials, including software with practice test items, are available to download from this website. <a href="/Examinations/practice_materials.html">Learn more </a></p>
<p> </p>
<p></p>
<p>Click on the links to the right to view sections of the Step 2 CK content description in hypertext format. </p>
<p>Step 2 Clinical Knowledge (Step 2 CK) consists of multiple-choice questions prepared by examination committees composed of faculty members, teachers, investigators, and clinicians with recognized prominence in their respective fields. Committee members are selected to provide broad representation from the academic, practice, and licensing communities across the United States and Canada. Test questions focus on the principles of clinical science that are deemed important for the practice of medicine under supervision in postgraduate training. The examination is constructed from an integrated content outline that organizes clinical science material along two dimensions.</p>
<p>Normal Conditions and Disease categories (Dimension 1) form the main axis for organizing the outline. The first section deals with normal growth and development, basic concepts, and general principles. The remaining sections deal with individual disorders.</p>
<p>Sections focusing on individual disorders are subdivided according to Physician Task (Dimension 2). The first set of physician tasks, Promoting Preventive Medicine and Health Maintenance, encompasses the assessment of risk factors, appreciation of epidemiologic data, and the application of primary and secondary preventive measures.</p>
<p>The second set of tasks, Understanding Mechanisms of Disease, encompasses etiology, pathophysiology, and effects of treatment modalities in the broadest sense. </p>
<p>The third set of tasks, Establishing a Diagnosis, pertains to interpretation of history and physical findings and the results of laboratory, imaging, and other studies to determine the most likely diagnosis or the most appropriate next step in diagnosis.</p>
<p>The fourth set of tasks, Applying Principles of Management, concerns the approach to care of patients with chronic and acute conditions in ambulatory and inpatient settings. Questions in this category will focus on the same topics covered in the diagnosis sections.</p>
<p>The diseases noted in the outline do not represent an all-inclusive registry of disorders about which questions may be asked. They reflect the development of a "High-Impact Disease List" that includes common problems, less common problems where early detection or treatability are important considerations, and noteworthy exemplars of pathophysiology. Questions are generally, but not exclusively, focused on the listed disorders. In addition, not all listed topics are included on each examination.</p>
<p>The Step 2 CK content outline is not intended as a curriculum development or study guide. It provides a flexible structure for test construction that can readily accommodate new topics, emerging content domains, and shifts in emphases. The categorizations and content coverage are subject to change. Broadly based learning that establishes a strong general foundation of understanding of concepts and principles in the clinical sciences is the best preparation for the examination.</p>
<p>For a detailed description of examination content areas, select any of the topic areas shown under STEP 2 CK Content Outline from the menu on the right. </p>
<p> Click on the links to the right to view sections of the booklet in hypertext format. </p>
<p>The United States Medical Licensing Examination (USMLE), through its three Steps (Step 1, Step 2, and Step 3), assesses a physician's ability to apply knowledge, concepts, and principles, and to demonstrate fundamental patient-centered skills that are important in health and disease and that constitute the basis of safe and effective patient care.</p>
<p>Results of the USMLE are reported to medical licensing authorities in the United States and its territories for use in granting the initial license to practice medicine. The USMLE is sponsored by the Federation of State Medical Boards (FSMB) and the National Board of Medical Examiners (NBME). </p>
<p>Step 2 of the USMLE assesses the ability of examinees to apply medical knowledge, skills, and understanding of clinical science essential for the provision of patient care under supervision, and includes emphasis on health promotion and disease prevention. Step 2 ensures that due attention is devoted to the principles of clinical sciences and basic patient-
centered skills that provide the foundation for the safe and effective practice of medicine.</p>
<p>There are two components of Step 2, Clinical Knowledge (CK) and Clinical Skills (CS). Step 2 CK uses the multiple-choice examination format to test clinical knowledge. Step 2 CS uses standardized patients to test medical students and graduates on their ability to gather information from patients, perform physical examinations, and communicate their findings to patients and colleagues.</p>
<p>This document is intended to help examinees prepare for the Step 2 CS component of the USMLE. Persons preparing to take the Step 2 CS examination should also view the video available at the <a href="../../index.html">USMLE website</a>.</p>
<p>Information on eligibility, registration, and scheduling is available in the USMLE<em> </em><a href="../../General_Information/general_information_bulletin.html"><em>Bulletin of Information</em></a>. Students and graduates of international medical schools must also consult the ECFMG <em>Information Booklet</em> and the <a href="http://www.ecfmg.org/">ECFMG website</a>.</p>
<p>The information in this document, as well as other materials, is available at the USMLE website and also via CD from your registration entity. Changes in the USMLE program may occur after the release of this document. <strong>If changes occur, information will be posted on the USMLE website. You must obtain the most recent information to ensure an accurate understanding of current USMLE policy</strong>.</p>
<div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>STEP 2 CK Content Description</h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<h2><strong>General Principles</strong></h2>&#xD;
	<p><strong>Infancy and Childhood </strong></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Normal growth and development</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Adolescence</strong> </p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Sexuality; separation from parents/autonomy;&#xD;
			physical changes of puberty</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Senescence </strong></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Normal physical and mental changes associated&#xD;
			with aging</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Medical Ethics and Jurisprudence </strong></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Consent and informed consent to treatment (eg,&#xD;
			full disclosure, alternate therapies, risks and benefits,&#xD;
					life-support, advance directives, health care&#xD;
			proxy)&#xD;
					and research issues (eg, consent, placebos, conflict&#xD;
					of interest, vulnerable populations)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Physician-patient&#xD;
			  relationship (eg, truth-telling, confidentiality, privacy,&#xD;
			  autonomy, public reporting)&#xD;
					  and birth-related issues (eg, prenatal diagnosis,&#xD;
abortion, maternal-fetal conflict)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Death and dying (eg, diagnosing death, organ&#xD;
			  donation, euthanasia, physician-assisted suicide) and&#xD;
palliative care (eg, hospice, pain management, family counseling,&#xD;
						psychosocial and spiritual issues, fear and&#xD;
loneliness)</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Applied Biostatistics and Clinical Epidemiology </strong></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Understanding statistical concepts of measurement&#xD;
			in medical practice</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Interpretation of the medical literature</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Systems-Based Practice and Patient Safety</strong></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Systems-based practice and quality improvement (microsystems and teams including hand-offs, standardization of processes, reducing deviance)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Patient safety, medical errors and near misses (sentinel events, problem identification, root cause analysis)</li>&#xD;
		</ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
&#xD;
	<h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<h2>Infectious and Parasitic Diseases </h2>&#xD;
	<p>(Topic covered under each organ system)</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Neoplasms</h2>&#xD;
        <p>(Topic covered under each organ system)</p>&#xD;
		<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Immunologic Disorders </h2>&#xD;
		<p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance</strong></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Anaphylaxis and other allergic&#xD;
			  reactions </li>&#xD;
		  <li>HIV infection/AIDS</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Immunization&#xD;
				against infectious agents (including infants, children,&#xD;
adults,&#xD;
the elderly; patients having compromised immune systems)</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease </strong></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Abnormalities of cell-mediated immunity </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Abnormalities&#xD;
			  of humoral immunity </li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Diagnosis</strong> </p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Anaphylactic reactions and shock</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Connective tissue disorders&#xD;
			  (eg, mixed connective tissue disease and systemic lupus&#xD;
			  erythematosus)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>HIV infection/AIDS; deficiencies of cell-mediated&#xD;
			  immunity</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Deficiencies of humoral immunity; combined&#xD;
			  immune deficiency </li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Principles of Management</strong><br/><em>(With emphasis on&#xD;
		  topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Pharmacotherapy only </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			  steps) </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Treatment only </li>&#xD;
		</ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline</h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Diseases of the Blood and Blood-forming Organs </h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance </strong></p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Anemia (iron deficiency,&#xD;
			vitamin-related, drug-induced, sickle cell)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Infection(systemic)</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease</strong> </p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Red cell disorders</li>&#xD;
			<li>Coagulation disorders </li>&#xD;
			<li>White cell disorders, including&#xD;
				leukopenia, agranulocytosis, and neoplasms</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Diagnosis</strong> </p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Anemia, disorders of red cells, hemoglobin,&#xD;
			  and iron metabolism (eg, blood loss; iron deficiency&#xD;
			  anemia,&#xD;
				nutritional deficiencies; pernicious anemia,&#xD;
			  other megaloblastic anemias; hemolytic anemia;&#xD;
			  anemia associated&#xD;
				with chronic disease; aplastic anemia, pancytopenia;&#xD;
				thalassemia; sickle cell disease; polycythemia&#xD;
			vera; hemochromatosis)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Bleeding disorders, coagulopathies,&#xD;
			  thrombocytopenia (eg, hemophilia, von Willebrand&#xD;
			  disease; qualitative and quantitative platelet&#xD;
			  deficiencies;&#xD;
				disseminated intravascular coagulation; hypofibrinogenemia;&#xD;
				immune thrombocytopenic purpura; hemolytic-uremic&#xD;
			syndrome) </li>&#xD;
			<li> Neoplastic&#xD;
			  disorders (eg, Hodgkin disease,&#xD;
				non-Hodgkin lymphomas; acute leukemia&#xD;
				in children; acute leukemia in adults; chronic&#xD;
				leukemic&#xD;
			states; mycosis fungoides; multiple myeloma)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Eosinophilia&#xD;
				and reactions to transfusion of blood components&#xD;
				(including complications) and leukopenic&#xD;
			  disorders, agranulocytosis</li>&#xD;
			<li>Infection (eg, sepsis,&#xD;
				malaria, mononucleosis)</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Principles of Management</strong><br/><em>(With emphasis&#xD;
		  on topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Pharmacotherapy only </li>&#xD;
			<li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			steps) </li>&#xD;
			<li>Treatment only</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline</h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Mental Disorders </h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance</strong></p>                   &#xD;
		<ul><li>Early identification and&#xD;
			  intervention (eg, suicide potential, depression, alcohol/substance&#xD;
			  abuse, family involvement&#xD;
				in schizophrenia)</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease</strong> </p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Biologic markers of mental disorders and mental&#xD;
			retardation syndromes</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Intended/unintended effects of therapeutic&#xD;
			  interventions, including effects of drugs on neurotransmitters</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Diagnosis </strong></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Mental disorders usually first diagnosed in&#xD;
			infancy, childhood, or adolescence (eg, mental retardation;&#xD;
			communication&#xD;
					disorders; pervasive developmental disorders;&#xD;
			attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder; disruptive&#xD;
			disorders; tic disorders; elimination&#xD;
				disorders)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Substance-related disorders (eg, alcohol&#xD;
			  and other substances)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Schizophrenia and other psychotic&#xD;
			  disorders</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Mood disorders (eg, bipolar disorders; major&#xD;
			  unipolar depressive disorders; dysthymic disorder;&#xD;
mood disorder due to a general medical condition; medication-induced&#xD;
				mood disorder)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Anxiety disorders (eg, panic&#xD;
			  disorder; phobia; obsessive-compulsive disorder; post-traumatic&#xD;
			  stress disorder;&#xD;
generalized anxiety disorder; acute stress disorder; separation&#xD;
							anxiety disorder; anxiety due to a general&#xD;
medical condition; substance-induced anxiety disorder)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Somatoform disorders&#xD;
			  (eg, factitious disorder; somatization disorder; pain&#xD;
			  disorder; conversion disorder; hypochondriasis)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Other&#xD;
			  disorders/conditions (eg, sexual and gender identity&#xD;
			  disorders; personality disorders; child, spouse, elder&#xD;
			  abuse; eating disorders;&#xD;
adjustment disorders;&#xD;
		dissociative disorders; psychological factors affecting medical&#xD;
conditions)</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Principles of Management </strong><br/><em>(With emphasis on topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Pharmacotherapy only </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			  steps) </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Treatment only </li>&#xD;
		</ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline</h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Diseases of the Nervous System and Special Senses </h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance </strong>  </p>                        &#xD;
		  <ul><li>Cerebrovascular disease,&#xD;
			cerebral infarction</li>&#xD;
			<li>Nutritional deficiencies,&#xD;
				  toxic injuries, and occupational disorders&#xD;
				including lead, carbon monoxide,&#xD;
and organophosphate poisoning</li>&#xD;
			<li>Infection involving the nervous&#xD;
			system, eyes, or ears </li>&#xD;
			<li>Degenerative and demyelinating&#xD;
				  disorders, including Alzheimer disease&#xD;
				  and multiple sclerosis</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease</strong> </p>&#xD;
			<ul><li>Localizing&#xD;
			  anatomy:&#xD;
				<ul><li> brain and&#xD;
				  special senses</li>&#xD;
				  <li> brain&#xD;
					  stem</li>&#xD;
				  <li> spinal cord</li>&#xD;
				  <li> neuromuscular&#xD;
						  system</li>&#xD;
				</ul></li>&#xD;
			  <li>Anatomy of cerebral&#xD;
			  circulation</li>&#xD;
			  <li> Increased&#xD;
				intracranial pressure&#xD;
				and altered state of&#xD;
			  consciousness</li>&#xD;
			  <li> Infection</li>&#xD;
			  <li>Degenerative/developmental&#xD;
				  and metabolic disorders</li>&#xD;
			</ul><p> <strong>Diagnosis</strong> </p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Disorders of the eye (eg, blindness;&#xD;
			  glaucoma; infection; papilledema; optic atrophy;&#xD;
			  retinal disorders; diabetic&#xD;
				retinopathy; diplopia; cataract; neoplasms; vascular&#xD;
				disorders; uveitis; iridocyclitis; traumatic,&#xD;
			  toxic injury; toxoplasmosis)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Disorders of the ear,&#xD;
			  olfaction, and taste (eg, deafness, hearing loss,&#xD;
			  otitis, mastoiditis; vertigo, tinnitus,&#xD;
				Meniere disease; acoustic neuroma; traumatic,&#xD;
				toxic injury)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Disorders of the nervous system:&#xD;
			  <ul><li>paroxysmal disorders&#xD;
				  (eg, headache; trigeminal neuralgia; seizure&#xD;
				  disorders; syncope)</li>&#xD;
				<li> cerebrovascular disease&#xD;
				  (eg, intracerebral hemorrhage; ischemic disorders;&#xD;
				  aneurysm,&#xD;
				   subarachnoid hemorrhage;&#xD;
					cavernous sinus thrombosis)</li>&#xD;
				<li> traumatic, toxic&#xD;
				  injury; including lead, carbon monoxide, and&#xD;
				  organophosphate poisoning</li>&#xD;
				<li> infections (eg, bacterial,&#xD;
				  fungal, viral, opportunistic infection in immunocompromised&#xD;
					patients; Lyme&#xD;
					disease; abscess; neurosyphilis; Guillain-Barr&#xE9; syndrome)</li>&#xD;
				<li> neoplasms (eg, primary; metastatic; neurofibromatosis)</li>&#xD;
				<li> metabolic disorders (eg, metabolic encephalopathy,&#xD;
					vitamin B<sub>12</sub> [cobalamin] deficiency,&#xD;
				  vitamin B<sub>1</sub> [thiamine] deficiency; coma, confusion,&#xD;
				  delirium, dementia)</li>&#xD;
				<li> degenerative&#xD;
				  and developmental disorders (eg, Alzheimer&#xD;
					disease; Huntington disease; parkinsonism;&#xD;
					amyotrophic lateral sclerosis; Tay-Sachs&#xD;
					disease; multiple sclerosis; cerebral palsy;&#xD;
					dyslexia)</li>&#xD;
				<li> neuromuscular disorders, gait abnormalities,&#xD;
					  and disorders relating to the spine and&#xD;
				  spinal nerve&#xD;
					  roots (eg, myasthenia gravis; muscular&#xD;
				  dystrophy; peripheral neuropathy; neck pain;&#xD;
				  cervical&#xD;
					  radiculopathy; lumbosacral radiculopathy;&#xD;
					  spinal stenosis)</li>&#xD;
				<li> sleep disorders (eg, narcolepsy,&#xD;
					idiopathic hypersomnolence, restless legs&#xD;
				  syndrome, REM sleep behavior disorder,&#xD;
						circadian rhythm sleep disorder, sleep&#xD;
						apnea)</li>&#xD;
			  </ul></li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p> <strong>Principles of Management</strong> <br/><em>(With emphasis on topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Pharmacotherapy&#xD;
			only </li>&#xD;
			<li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			  steps) </li>&#xD;
			<li>Treatment only</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Cardiovascular Disorders </h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance</strong></p>                    &#xD;
		<ul><li>Arterial hypertension</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Atherosclerosis&#xD;
				and coronary artery disease; hyperlipidemia</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Prevention&#xD;
				of rheumatic heart disease, thromboembolic disease,&#xD;
					  pulmonary emboli, bacterial endocarditis</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease</strong> </p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Cardiac output, resistance, central venous&#xD;
			pressure</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Valvular stenosis, incompetence</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Congenital heart disease</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Regulation of blood pressure</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Disorders of the arteries&#xD;
			  and veins</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Diagnosis</strong> </p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Dysrhythmias; palpitations, syncope (eg, premature&#xD;
					beats; paroxysmal tachycardias; atrial flutter&#xD;
			and fibrillation; bradycardias; ventricular fibrillation;&#xD;
				cardiac arrest) </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Heart failure (congestive, diastolic,&#xD;
			  systolic dysfunction), dyspnea, fatigue, peripheral&#xD;
			edema of cardiac&#xD;
origin (eg, chronic heart failure; cor pulmonale)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Ischemic heart disease; chest&#xD;
			  pain of cardiac origin (eg, angina pectoris; coronary&#xD;
			  insufficiency;&#xD;
myocardial infarction)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Diseases of the myocardium (eg, hypertrophic; myocarditis)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Diseases&#xD;
			  of the pericardium (eg, acute pericarditis; chronic&#xD;
			constrictive pericardiopathy; pericardial&#xD;
effusion; pericardial tamponade)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Valvular heart disease (eg, acute rheumatic&#xD;
			  fever; mitral and aortic valve disorders; infective&#xD;
endocarditis)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Congenital cardiovascular disease (eg, patent ductus&#xD;
							  arteriosus; atrial septal defect; ventricular&#xD;
septal defect; endocardial cushion defect; tetralogy of Fallot;&#xD;
				coarctation of the aorta)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Systemic hypotension,&#xD;
			  hypovolemia, cardiogenic shock; cyanosis</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Arterial hypertension&#xD;
			  (eg, essential; secondary) </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Atherosclerosis - lipoproteins</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Disorders of the great&#xD;
			  vessels (eg, dissecting aortic aneurysm; ruptured aneurysm;&#xD;
aortoiliac disease)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Peripheral arterial vascular diseases, vasculitis (eg,&#xD;
									  polyarteritis; temporal arteritis;&#xD;
arteriovenous fistula)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Diseases of the veins, peripheral edema (eg, varicose&#xD;
									  veins; thrombophlebitis; deep&#xD;
venous thrombosis)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Traumatic injury</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Principles of Management</strong><br/><em>(With emphasis on topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Pharmacotherapy only </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			  steps) </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Treatment only</li>&#xD;
		</ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Diseases of the Respiratory System </h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance </strong></p>&#xD;
			<ul><li>Chronic bronchitis, asthma,&#xD;
				  emphysema, carcinoma of the larynx, carcinoma of the&#xD;
				  lung; pulmonary aspiration, atelectasis;&#xD;
					tuberculosis</li>&#xD;
			</ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease </strong></p>&#xD;
			<ul><li>Ventilatory dysfunction (eg, obstructive disorders:&#xD;
						asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease,&#xD;
				cystic fibrosis, bronchitis, bronchiectasis, emphysema)</li>&#xD;
			  <li>Respiratory&#xD;
				  failure, acute and chronic, including oxygenation failure&#xD;
				  (eg, interstitial pneumonitis, pulmonary&#xD;
edema, acute respiratory distress syndrome, ventilation failure)</li>&#xD;
			  <li>Circulatory&#xD;
				  dysfunction</li>&#xD;
			  <li>Neoplastic disorders</li>&#xD;
			</ul><p><strong>Diagnosis</strong> </p>&#xD;
			<ul><li>Disorders of the nose, paranasal sinuses, pharynx,&#xD;
						larynx, and trachea (eg, rhinitis; pharyngitis,&#xD;
				tonsillitis, peritonsillar abscess; thrush; sinusitis;&#xD;
				acute laryngotracheitis;&#xD;
						epiglottitis; carcinoma of the larynx; laryngeal/pharyngeal&#xD;
						obstruction; trauma; tracheoesophageal fistula)</li>&#xD;
			  <li> Infections of the lung (eg, acute bronchiolitis; pneumonia;&#xD;
						tuberculosis) </li>&#xD;
			  <li> Obstructive airways disease (eg,&#xD;
				  chronic bronchitis, bronchiectasis; asthma, bronchospasm,&#xD;
				  wheezing;&#xD;
emphysema, <font face="symbol">a</font>1-antitrypsin&#xD;
deficiency; cystic fibrosis)</li>&#xD;
			  <li> Atelectasis, pulmonary&#xD;
				  aspiration</li>&#xD;
			  <li> Pneumothorax, hemothorax, traumatic injury&#xD;
				  to the lungs and disorders involving the pleura (eg,&#xD;
				  pleurisy;&#xD;
pleural effusion)</li>&#xD;
			  <li>Pneumoconiosis, fibrosing or restrictive pulmonary&#xD;
							  disorders (eg, asbestosis; silicosis; sarcoidosis)</li>&#xD;
			  <li> Respiratory failure, hypoxia, hypercapnia, dyspnea&#xD;
				(eg, respiratory distress syndrome of the&#xD;
newborn; acute respiratory distress syndrome; acute and&#xD;
chronic respiratory failure; drowning) </li>&#xD;
			  <li> Pulmonary vascular disorders&#xD;
				  (eg, pulmonary embolism; pulmonary hypertension; pulmonary&#xD;
				  edema) </li>&#xD;
			  <li> Neoplastic disorders of the lungs and pleura&#xD;
				  (eg, primary tumors; metastatic tumors)</li>&#xD;
			</ul><p><strong>Principles of Management </strong><br/><em>(With emphasis on topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
			<ul><li>Pharmacotherapy only </li>&#xD;
			  <li> Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
				  steps) </li>&#xD;
			  <li> Treatment only</li>&#xD;
			</ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Nutritional and Digestive Disorders </h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance</strong></p>                    &#xD;
		<ul><li> Screening (eg, cancer)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Viral hepatitis&#xD;
				and alcohol-related hepatopathy</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease</strong> </p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Malabsorption/malnutrition</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Jaundice</li>&#xD;
		  <li> Infections/parasites</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Obstruction/mechanical</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Diagnosis</strong> </p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Disorders of the mouth, salivary glands, oropharynx,&#xD;
					and esophagus (eg, dental disorders; disorders&#xD;
			of the salivary glands; esophageal reflux; dysphagia;&#xD;
			motility&#xD;
					disorders of the esophagus; hiatal hernia; carcinoma&#xD;
					of the esophagus)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Disorders of the stomach, small&#xD;
			  intestine, colon, and rectum/anus (eg, gastritis; peptic&#xD;
			  ulcer disease;&#xD;
congenital disorders; malabsorption; appendicitis; granulomatous&#xD;
					  enterocolitis; ischemic colitis; irritable&#xD;
			bowel syndrome; diverticula; colonic polyps; ulcerative&#xD;
			colitis; peritonitis;&#xD;
					  bowel obstruction, volvulus, intussusception;&#xD;
hernia; necrotizing enterocolitis; infection; carcinoma of&#xD;
					  the stomach, colon, and rectum; antibiotic-associated&#xD;
					  colitis; hemorrhoids; anal fissures; anal fistula;&#xD;
					  perianal/perirectal abscess)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Disorders of the&#xD;
			  pancreas (eg, pancreatitis; pseudocyst; carcinoma of&#xD;
			  the pancreas)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Disorders of the liver and biliary system&#xD;
			  (eg, hepatitis; cirrhosis; hepatic failure, hepatic&#xD;
			encephalopathy, jaundice; portal hypertension; ascites,&#xD;
			esophageal&#xD;
						  varices; cholelithiasis; cholecystitis;&#xD;
			hepatic abscess, subphrenic abscess; neoplasms of the&#xD;
			liver; storage&#xD;
				diseases; neoplasms of the biliary tract)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Traumatic&#xD;
			  injury and poisoning (including drain cleaner ingestion)</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Principles of Management</strong> <br/><em>(With emphasis on topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Pharmacotherapy only </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			  steps) </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Treatment only</li>&#xD;
		</ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Gynecologic Disorders </h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance</strong> </p>                          &#xD;
		  <ul><li>Postmenarchal/reproductive</li>&#xD;
			<li>Peri/postmenopausal</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease</strong> </p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Infections (eg, vulvovaginitis; pelvic&#xD;
			  inflammatory disease; toxic shock; sexually transmitted&#xD;
			  disease;&#xD;
				endometritis; urethritis; Bartholin gland&#xD;
			abscess; abscess of the breast; mastitis)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Urinary&#xD;
			  incontinence and obstruction</li>&#xD;
			<li>Menstrual and endocrinologic&#xD;
				disorders; infertility </li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Diagnosis</strong> </p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Pelvic&#xD;
				  relaxation and urinary incontinence (eg, urinary&#xD;
				  tract infection;&#xD;
				  uterovaginal prolapse; cystocele,&#xD;
			rectocele, urethrocele) </li>&#xD;
			<li>Neoplasms (eg, cervical&#xD;
			  dysplasia, cancer; leiomyomata uteri; endometrial&#xD;
			  cancer; ovarian neoplasms;&#xD;
neoplastic disorders of the breast; vulvar neoplasms)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Benign conditions of the&#xD;
			breast</li>&#xD;
			<li>Menstrual and endocrinologic disorders (eg,&#xD;
			  amenorrhea [including undiagnosed pregnancy]; abnormal&#xD;
uterine bleeding; dysmenorrhea; menopausal, postmenopausal&#xD;
				  disorders [osteoporosis]; premenstrual syndrome;&#xD;
				  hirsutism, virilization; ovarian disorders&#xD;
[ovarian failure, polycystic ovarian syndrome])</li>&#xD;
			<li>Sexual abuse and rape</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Principles of Management </strong><br/><em>(With emphasis on topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Pharmacotherapy&#xD;
			only </li>&#xD;
			<li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			  steps) </li>&#xD;
			<li>Treatment only</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline</h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Renal, Urinary, and Male Reproductive Systems </h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance</strong></p>         &#xD;
		<ul><li> Infection (eg, urinary&#xD;
			  tract, sexually transmitted diseases [male])</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Acute and&#xD;
				chronic renal failure including risk factors and&#xD;
			  prevention and methods of limiting progression</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Male&#xD;
				health maintenance examination (eg, testicular, prostatic) &#xD;
		  </li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease</strong></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Disorders of the male reproductive&#xD;
				system</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Urinary incontinence and obstruction, enuresis</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Renal&#xD;
			  insufficiency/failure</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Electrolyte and water metabolism&#xD;
			  and acid-base balance</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Diagnosis</strong> </p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Disorders of the male reproductive system (eg,&#xD;
			infections; torsion of the testis; undescended testicle;&#xD;
			neoplasms&#xD;
					of the testis; benign prostatic hyperplasia;&#xD;
			carcinoma of the prostate; hypospadias; hydrocele, varicocele;&#xD;
				urethral stricture, impotence, premature ejaculation)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Disorders&#xD;
			  of the urinary bladder and urinary collecting system&#xD;
			  (eg, cystitis; pyelitis; dysuria, hematuria,&#xD;
					  pyuria; carcinoma of the bladder; urolithiasis;&#xD;
ureteral reflux; neurogenic bladder; urinary incontinence; enuresis;&#xD;
				obstruction; hydronephrosis)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Disorders of the&#xD;
			  kidneys (eg, pyelonephritis; glomerulonephritis; interstitial&#xD;
			  nephropathy; renal insufficiency&#xD;
and failure; oliguria, anuria, azotemia, uremia, renal osteodystrophy;&#xD;
						hypertensive renal disease; lupus nephritis;&#xD;
inherited disorders)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Traumatic injury</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Principles of Management </strong><br/><em>(With emphasis on topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Pharmacotherapy only </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			  steps) </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Treatment only</li>&#xD;
		</ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Disorders of Pregnancy, Childbirth, and the Puerperium </h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance</strong></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Prenatal care&#xD;
				(eg, nutrition; prevention of iron deficiency; prevention&#xD;
				of vitamin deficiency; Rh immunoglobulin prophylaxis;&#xD;
				prenatal diagnosis; teratology, diabetes mellitus,&#xD;
			  urinary tract infection, <font face="symbol">a</font>-fetoprotein,&#xD;
			  rubella, genital herpes, streptococcal infections)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Assessment&#xD;
				of the at-risk pregnancy; risk of preterm labor</li>&#xD;
		  <li> Intrapartum&#xD;
				care; signs of fetal compromise</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Contraception; sterilization;&#xD;
				prevention of pregnancy after rape</li>								&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease</strong> </p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Placenta, placental dysfunction</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Pregnancy and labor,&#xD;
			  including infection</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Postpartum disorders, including&#xD;
			  infection</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Fetus and newborn</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Diagnosis</strong> </p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Pregnancy and labor, including obstetric&#xD;
			  complications (eg, ectopic pregnancy; spontaneous abortion/septic&#xD;
			  abortion; hypertension; third-trimester bleeding; hydramnios;&#xD;
			  preterm labor, premature rupture of the membranes,&#xD;
			normal labor; multiple gestation; intrapartum fetal distress/fetal&#xD;
			  death; maternal mortality; fetal growth and development&#xD;
			  abnormalities; congenital abnormalities; gestational&#xD;
			trophoblastic&#xD;
			  disease)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Nonobstetric complications of pregnancy (eg,&#xD;
			  major medical complications and preexisting medical&#xD;
			conditions; surgical complications; hyperemesis gravidarum)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Complications&#xD;
			  of the puerperium (eg, problems with breast-feeding;&#xD;
			  postpartum hemorrhage; postpartum sepsis; postpartum&#xD;
			  depression, psychosis; mastitis;&#xD;
venous thromboembolism)</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Principles of Management </strong><br/><em>(With emphasis on topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Pharmacotherapy only </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			  steps) </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Treatment only</li>&#xD;
		</ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline</h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Disorders of the Skin and Subcutaneous Tissues</h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance</strong></p>                          &#xD;
		  <ul><li>Epidemiology and prevention&#xD;
				of skin disorders secondary to exposure to the&#xD;
				sun; contact dermatitis and drug&#xD;
				  reactions; decubitus ulcers; dermatophytic&#xD;
				skin disorders</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease</strong> </p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Skin disorders, including cancer, infections,&#xD;
			  and inflammatory disorders</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Diagnosis </strong></p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Infections (eg, herpes simplex, herpes&#xD;
			  zoster, chickenpox; cellulitis, carbuncle, abscess,&#xD;
			  gangrene; dermatophytoses;&#xD;
				  pilonidal cyst; viral warts; decubitus ulcers)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Neoplasms (eg, squamous cell carcinoma; melanoma;&#xD;
				  actinic keratosis, basal cell carcinoma; pigmented&#xD;
			nevi; hemangiomas)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Other skin disorders (eg,&#xD;
				industrial, occupational, and atopic dermatitis;&#xD;
				psoriasis; seborrhea;&#xD;
acne)</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Principles of Management<br/></strong><em>(With emphasis on topics covered in&#xD;
		  Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Pharmacotherapy only </li>&#xD;
			<li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			  steps) </li>&#xD;
			<li>Treatment only</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline</h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Diseases of the Musculoskeletal System and Connective Tissue </h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance</strong></p>                    &#xD;
		<ul><li>Epidemiology, impact, and&#xD;
			  prevention of degenerative joint and disc disease</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Prevention&#xD;
				of disability due to musculoskeletal disorders or&#xD;
			  infection (eg, osteomyelitis; septic arthritis;&#xD;
Lyme disease; gonococcal tenosynovitis)</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease</strong> </p>&#xD;
		<ul><li> Infections</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Nerve compressions and degenerative, metabolic,&#xD;
			  and nutritional disorders</li>&#xD;
		  <li> Inherited, congenital, or&#xD;
			  developmental disorders </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Inflammatory or immunologic&#xD;
			  disorders</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Diagnosis </strong></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Infections (eg, osteomyelitis; septic arthritis;&#xD;
			Lyme disease; gonococcal tenosynovitis)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Degenerative,&#xD;
			  metabolic, and nutritional disorders (eg, degenerative&#xD;
			  joint disease; degenerative disc&#xD;
				disease; gout; rickets)</li>&#xD;
		  <li> Inherited, congenital,&#xD;
			  or developmental disorders (eg, congenital hip dysplasia;&#xD;
			  phocomelia; osteochondritis;&#xD;
					  slipped capital femoral epiphysis; scoliosis;&#xD;
syringomyelia, dislocated hip in infantile spinal muscular atrophy)</li>&#xD;
		  <li> Inflammatory, immunologic, and other disorders (eg,&#xD;
			  polymyalgia rheumatica; lupus arthritis; polymyositis-dermatomyositis;&#xD;
						rheumatoid arthritis; ankylosing spondylitis;&#xD;
					bursitis;&#xD;
						tendinitis; myofascial pain; fibromyalgia;&#xD;
					shoulder-hand syndrome; Dupuytren contracture;&#xD;
					Paget&#xD;
				disease)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Neoplasms (eg, osteosarcoma; metastases&#xD;
				to bone; pulmonary osteoarthropathy)</li>&#xD;
		  <li>Traumatic&#xD;
			  injury and nerve compression and injury (eg, fractures,&#xD;
			  sprains, dislocations, carpal&#xD;
tunnel syndrome; cauda equina syndrome, low back pain)</li>&#xD;
		</ul><p><strong>Principles of Management</strong><br/><em>(With emphasis on topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		<ul><li>Pharmacotherapy only </li>&#xD;
		  <li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			  steps) </li>&#xD;
		  <li> Treatment only</li>&#xD;
		</ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Endocrine and Metabolic Disorders</h2>&#xD;
        <p><strong>Health and Health Maintenance </strong></p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Diabetes mellitus,&#xD;
				including prevention of morbidity and mortality&#xD;
			due to complications </li>&#xD;
			<li>Screening (eg, cancer)&#xD;
			</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Mechanisms of Disease</strong> </p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Thyroid function</li>&#xD;
			<li>Diabetes mellitus and carbohydrate&#xD;
			metabolism</li>&#xD;
			<li>Parathyroid and calcium metabolism</li>&#xD;
			<li>Pituitary and&#xD;
			  hypothalamic function</li>&#xD;
			<li>Adrenal function</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Diagnosis </strong></p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Thyroid disorders (eg, nodule; carcinoma;&#xD;
			  acquired hypothyroidism; thyroiditis; thyrotoxicosis;&#xD;
			  congenital&#xD;
			hypothyroidism; goiter)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Diabetes mellitus (eg,&#xD;
			  type 1, type 2; ketoacidosis; hyperosmolar coma;&#xD;
			chronic complications)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Parathyroid and calcium disorders&#xD;
			  (eg, hyperparathyroidism; hypoparathyroidism),&#xD;
			  and hypoglycemia and hyperinsulinism&#xD;
			(eg, iatrogenic; insulinoma) </li>&#xD;
			<li>Pituitary, hypothalamic&#xD;
			  disorders (eg, diabetes insipidus; inappropriate&#xD;
			  ADH secretion; panhypopituitarism;&#xD;
			acromegaly)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Adrenal disorders (eg, corticoadrenal&#xD;
			  insufficiency; Cushing syndrome; adrenogenital&#xD;
			  syndrome; hyperaldosteronism; pheochromocytoma)</li>&#xD;
			<li>Heat-related&#xD;
				illness</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><p><strong>Principles of Management </strong><br/><em>(With emphasis on topics covered in Diagnosis)</em></p>&#xD;
		  <ul><li>Pharmacotherapy only </li>&#xD;
			<li>Management decision (treatment/diagnosis&#xD;
			  steps) </li>&#xD;
			<li> Treatment only</li>&#xD;
		  </ul><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Congenital Anomalies</h2>&#xD;
        <p><em>(Topic covered under each organ system)</em></p>&#xD;
		<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Conditions Originating in the Perinatal Period </h2>&#xD;
        <p><em>(Topic covered under <a href="pregnancy.html">Disorders of Pregnancy, Childbirth, and the Puerperium</a> )</em></p>&#xD;
		<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Symptoms, Signs, and Ill-defined Conditions</h2>&#xD;
        <p><em>(Topic covered under each organ system)</em></p>&#xD;
		<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
        <h1>STEP 2 CK Content Outline </h1>&#xD;
        <h2>Injury and Poisoning</h2>&#xD;
        <p><em>(Topic covered under each organ system)</em></p>&#xD;
		<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
<h1>Step 2 CS Case Development</h1>&#xD;
<h2>Standardized Patient-Based Examinations</h2>&#xD;
<p>The patients you will see are people trained to portray a clinical problem. This method of assessment is referred to as a standardized patient examination. The standardized patient-based testing method was established more than 35 years ago, and its procedures have been tested and validated in the United States and internationally.</p>&#xD;
<p>When you take the Step 2 CS examination, you will have the same opportunity as all other examinees to demonstrate your clinical skills proficiency. The examination is standardized, so that all examinees receive the same information when they ask standardized patients the same or similar questions. An ongoing mechanism of quality control is employed to ensure that the examination is fair to all. The quality control approach focuses on consistency in portrayal and scoring of the individual cases, and utilizes both observation of live encounters and review of digital recordings.</p>&#xD;
<h2>Examination Blueprint</h2>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>As part of the test development process, practicing physicians and medical educators develop and review cases to ensure that they are accurate and appropriate. These cases represent the kinds of patients and problems normally encountered during medical practice in the United States. Most cases are specifically designed to elicit a process of history taking and physical examination that demonstrates the examinee's ability to list and pursue various plausible &#xD;
diagnoses.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>The cases that make up each administration of the Step 2 CS examination are based upon an examination blueprint. An examination blueprint defines the requirements for each examination, regardless of where and when it is administered. The sample of cases selected for each examination reflects a balance of cases that is fair and equitable across all examinees. On any examination day, the set of cases will differ from the combination presented the day before or the following day, but each set of cases has a comparable degree of difficulty.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>The intent is to ensure that examinees encounter a broad spectrum of cases reflecting common and important symptoms and diagnoses. The criteria used to define the blueprint and create individual examinations focus primarily on presenting complaints and conditions. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Presentation categories include, but are not limited to, cardiovascular, constitutional, gastrointestinal, genitourinary, musculoskeletal, neurological, psychiatric, respiratory, and women's health. Examinees will see cases from some, but not all, of these categories. The selection of cases is also guided by specifications relating to acuity, age, gender, and type of physical findings presented in each case.</p>&#xD;
<p>Your Step 2 CS administration will include twelve patient encounters.  These include a very small number of nonscored patient encounters, which are added for pilot testing new cases and other research purposes.  Such cases are not counted in determining your score.</p>&#xD;
<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
      <h1>Description of the Examination </h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>When you arrive at the test center on the day of your examination, bring the Scheduling Permit you received when your registration was completed, your Confirmation Notice, and an unexpired, government-issued form of identification that includes a photograph and signature, such as a current driver's license or passport. Your name as it appears on your Scheduling Permit must match the name on your form(s) of identification exactly. The only acceptable differences are variations in capitalization; the presence of a middle name, middle initial, or suffix on one document and its absence on the other; or the presence of a middle name on one and middle initial on the other. </p>&#xD;
<p><strong>If you do not bring acceptable identification, you will not be admitted to the test</strong>. In that event, you must pay a fee to reschedule your test. Your rescheduled test date(s) must fall within your assigned eligibility period. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>The time you should arrive at the test center is listed in the Confirmation Notice you will print after scheduling your appointment. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Please note that, as part of the Step 2 CS registration process, you acknowledge and agree to abide by USMLE policies and procedures, including those related to confidentiality.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Please bring only necessary personal items with you to the center. You may not possess cellular telephones,&#xD;
watches of any type, pagers, personal digital assistants&#xD;
(PDAs), two-way communication devices, or notes or&#xD;
study materials of any kind at any time during the&#xD;
examination, including during breaks. These items must be stored during the examination. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Each test center contains a locked storage area with&#xD;
small open cubicles. Coat racks are also available.&#xD;
Each examinee is assigned one of the cubicles in&#xD;
which all personal items must be stored during the&#xD;
examination. Examinees are not permitted access to&#xD;
the cubicles at any time during the examination,&#xD;
including breaks. Luggage may not be stored in the&#xD;
center. There are no waiting facilities for spouses,&#xD;
family, or friends; plan to meet them elsewhere after&#xD;
the examination. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Wear comfortable, professional clothing and a white laboratory or clinic coat. The proctors will cover with adhesive tape anything on the laboratory coat that identifies either you or your institution. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>The only piece of medical equipment you may bring is an unenhanced standard stethoscope, which is subject to inspection by testing center staff. All other necessary medical equipment is provided in the examination rooms. Do not bring other medical equipment, such as reflex hammers, pen lights, or tuning forks to the testing center. If you forget to bring a laboratory coat or stethoscope, a limited number of coats and stethoscopes are available at each test center. However, it is strongly recommended that you bring your own.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>As more fully explained in the <em>Bulletin of Information</em>, unauthorized possession of personal items while you are in the secure areas of the testing center  is prohibited, and unauthorized items will be taken away. However, in certain limited circumstances, exceptions to this policy may be made for medical reasons, provided that permission is granted in advance of test administration.If you believe that&#xD;
you have a medical condition that requires you to use&#xD;
medication, an external appliance, or electronic device&#xD;
in the secure areas of the test center, you will need to&#xD;
submit a written request. Information on how to submit&#xD;
a request is available in the USMLE <em>Bulletin of&#xD;
Information</em>. Examples of appliances and devices to&#xD;
which this policy applies include non-standard stethoscopes,&#xD;
(eg, electronic or digitally amplified or otherwise&#xD;
enhanced non-standard stethoscopes), insulin&#xD;
pumps, inhalers, syringes, medications (oral, inhaled,&#xD;
injectable), TENS units, breast pumps, hearing aids,&#xD;
wheelchairs, canes, crutches, and casts. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Each examination session begins with an on-site orientation. <strong>If you arrive during the on-site orientation, you may be allowed to test; however, you will be required to sign a Late Admission Form. If you arrive after the on-site orientation, you will not be allowed to test</strong>. You will have to reschedule your testing appointment and will be required to pay the rescheduling fee.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>The clinical skills evaluation centers are secured facilities. Once you enter the secured area of the center for orientation, you may not leave that area until the examination is complete.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Throughout the examination day, staff members, wearing identifying name tags, will direct you through the examination. You must follow their instructions at all times.</p>&#xD;
	<h2>Examination Length</h2>&#xD;
	<p>Your Step 2 CS administration will include twelve patient encounters. The examination session lasts approximately 8 hours, and two breaks are provided. The first break is 30 minutes long; the second break is 15 minutes long. You may use the restrooms before the exam and during breaks. A light meal will be served during the first break. The test center is unable to accommodate special meal requests. However, you may  bring your own food, provided that no refrigeration or preparation is required. Smoking is prohibited throughout the center.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
    <h2>Equipment and Examinee Instructions</h2>&#xD;
	<p>The testing area of the clinical skills evaluation center consists of a series of examination rooms equipped with standard examination tables, commonly used diagnostic instruments (blood pressure cuffs, otoscopes, and ophthalmoscopes), non-latex gloves, sinks, and paper towels. Examination table heights are approximately 32-33 inches, and are not adjustable. Outside each examination room is a cubicle equipped with a computer, where you can compose the patient note.</p>&#xD;
	<p>There is a one-way observation window in each examination room. These are used for quality assurance, training, and research. </p>&#xD;
	<p>Before the first patient encounter, you will be provided with a clipboard, blank paper for taking notes, and a pen. There will be an announcement at the beginning of each patient encounter. When you hear the announcement you may review the patient information posted on the examination room door (examinee instructions). You may also make notes at this time. DO NOT write on the paper before the announcement that the patient encounter has begun. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
    <p>The examinee instruction sheet gives you specific instructions and indicates the patient's name, age, gender, and reason for visiting the doctor. It also indicates his or her vital signs, including heart rate, blood pressure, temperature (Celsius and Fahrenheit), and respiratory rate, unless instructions indicate otherwise. You can accept the vital signs on the examinee instruction sheet as accurate, and do not necessarily need to repeat them unless you believe the case specifically requires it. For instance, you may encounter patient problems or conditions that suggest the need to confirm or re-check the recorded vital signs and/or perform specific maneuvers in measuring the vital signs. However, if you do repeat the vital signs, with or without additional maneuvers, you should consider the vital signs that were originally listed as accurate when developing your differential diagnosis and work-up plan.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>You may encounter a case in which the examinee instructions include the results of a lab test. In this type of patient encounter the patient is returning for a follow-up appointment after undergoing testing.</p>&#xD;
	<h2>The Patient Encounter</h2>&#xD;
	<p>You will have 15 minutes for each patient encounter. </p>&#xD;
	<p>When you enter the room, you will usually encounter a standardized patient. By asking this patient relevant questions and performing a focused physical examination, you will be able to gather enough information to develop a preliminary differential diagnosis and a diagnostic work-up plan. </p>&#xD;
	<p>You will be expected to communicate with the standardized patients in a professional and empathetic manner. As you would when encountering real patients, you should answer any questions they may have, tell them what diagnoses you are considering, and advise them on what tests and studies you will order to clarify their diagnoses.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>The elements of medical history you need to obtain in each case will be determined by the nature of the patient's problems. Not every part of the history needs to be taken for every patient. Some patients may have acute problems, while others may have more chronic ones. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>You will not have time to do a complete physical examination on every patient, nor will it be necessary to do so. Pursue the relevant parts of the examination, based on the patient's problems and other information you obtain during the history taking.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>The cases are developed to present in a manner that simulates how patients present in real clinical settings. Therefore, most cases are designed realistically to present more than one diagnostic possibility. Based on the patient's presenting complaint and the additional information you obtain as you begin taking the history, you should consider all possible diagnoses and explore the relevant ones as time permits.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>If you are unsuccessful at Step 2 CS and must, therefore, repeat the examination, it is possible that during your repeat examination you will see similarities to cases or patients that you encountered on your prior attempt. <strong>Do not assume</strong> that the underlying problems are the same or that the encounter will unfold in exactly the same way. It is best if you approach each encounter, whether it seems familiar or not, with an open mind, responding appropriately to the information provided, the history gathered, and the results of the physical examination. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<h2>Physical Examination </h2>&#xD;
<p>You should perform physical examination maneuvers correctly and expect that there will be positive physical findings in some instances. Some may be simulated, but you should accept them as real and factor them into your evolving differential diagnoses. </p>&#xD;
<p>You should attend to appropriate hygiene and to patient comfort and modesty, as you would in the care of real patients. Female patients will be wearing bras, which you may ask them to loosen or move if necessary for a proper examination. </p>&#xD;
<p>With real patients in a normal clinical setting, it is possible to obtain meaningful information during your physical examination without being unnecessarily forceful in palpating, percussing, or carrying out other maneuvers that involve touching. Your approach to examining standardized patients should be no different. Standardized patients are subjected to repeated physical examinations during the Step 2 CS exam; <strong>it is critical that you apply no more than the amount of pressure that is appropriate</strong> during maneuvers such as abdominal examination, examination of the gall bladder and liver, eliciting CVA tenderness, examination of the ears with an otoscope, and examination of the throat with a tongue depressor.</p>&#xD;
<p>You should interact with the standardized patients as you would with any patients you may see with similar problems. The only exception is that certain parts of the physical examination MUST NOT BE DONE: rectal, pelvic, genitourinary, inguinal hernia, female breast, or corneal reflex examinations. If you believe one or more of these examinations are indicated, you should include them in your proposed diagnostic work-up. All other examination maneuvers are completely acceptable, including femoral pulse exam, inguinal node exam, back exam, and axillary exam.</p>&#xD;
<p>Another exception is that you should not swab the standardized patient&#x2019;s throat for a throat culture. If you believe that this diagnostic/laboratory test is indicated, include it on your proposed diagnostic workup. </p>&#xD;
<p>Excluding the restricted physical examination maneuvers, you should assume that you have consent to do a physical examination on all standardized patients, <strong>unless you are explicitly told not to do so</strong> as part of the examinee instructions for that case.</p>&#xD;
<p>Announcements will tell you when to begin the patient encounter, when there are 5 minutes remaining, and when the patient encounter is over. In some cases you may complete the patient encounter in fewer than 15 minutes. If so, you may leave the examination room early, but you are not permitted to re-enter. <strong>Be certain that you have obtained all necessary information before leaving the examination room</strong>. Re-entering an examination room after leaving will be considered misconduct.</p>&#xD;
<h2>Telephone Patient Encounters</h2>&#xD;
<p>Telephone patient encounters begin like all encounters; you will read a doorway instruction sheet that provides specific information about the patient. As with all patient encounters, as soon as you hear the announcement that the encounter has begun, you may make notes about the case before entering the examination room.</p>&#xD;
<p>When you enter the room, sit at the desk in front of the telephone.</p>&#xD;
<ul><li>Do not dial any numbers. </li>&#xD;
  <li>Push the speaker button by the yellow dot on the phone to be connected.</li>&#xD;
  <li>You will be permitted to make only one phone call. </li>&#xD;
  <li>Do not touch any buttons on the phone until you are ready to end the call - touching any buttons may disconnect you. </li>&#xD;
  <li>To end the call on a phone case, press the &#xD;
speaker button above the yellow dot.</li>&#xD;
  <li>You will not be allowed to call back after you end the call. </li>&#xD;
</ul><p>Obviously, physical examination of the patient is not possible for telephone encounters, and will not be required. However, for these cases, as for all others, you will have relevant information and instructions and will be able to take a history and ask questions. As with other cases, you will write a patient note after the encounter. Because no physical examination is possible for telephone cases, leave that section of the patient note blank.</p>&#xD;
<h2>The Patient Note</h2>&#xD;
	<p>Immediately after each patient encounter, you will have 10 minutes to complete a patient note. <strong>Note: If you leave the patient encounter early, you may use the additional time for the note</strong>. You will be asked to type (on a computer) a patient note similar to the medical record you would compose after seeing a patient in a clinic, office, or emergency department. </p>&#xD;
	<p><strong>IMPORTANT NOTE:</strong> Step 2 CS examinees will be required  to type patient notes beginning mid-2011. Examinees will not be permitted to  handwrite the note, unless technical difficulties on the test day make the  patient note typing program unavailable. Please check the USMLE website for information about the date  on which this change to the testing procedures will occur.</p>&#xD;
	<p>You should record pertinent medical history and physical examination findings obtained during the encounter, as well as your initial differential diagnoses. Finally, you will list the diagnostic studies you would order next for that particular patient. If you think a rectal, pelvic, genitourinary, female breast, or corneal reflex examination, or a throat swab, would have been indicated in the encounter, list it as part of your diagnostic workup. <strong>Treatment, consultations, or referrals should not be included in your work-up plan</strong>. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Appendix A illustrates a blank patient note screen. Appendix B provides sample patient note styles. A program for practicing typing the patient note is available on the USMLE website. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Occasionally, due to technical or administration problems, you will not be able to type the patient note  for one or more patient encounters. When this happens, examinees will be required to write their patient notes by hand. Appendix C illustrates a blank patient note page similar to what you will be asked to complete if you write the note by hand. All examinees should be prepared for the possibility that they may have to write one or more patient notes by hand. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Patient notes are rated by physicians who are well trained at reading notes and can interpret most handwriting. However, extreme illegibility will be a problem and can adversely impact a score. Everyone who writes patient notes by hand should make them as legible as possible.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>If you have a case for which you think no diagnostic workup is necessary, write "No studies indicated" rather than leaving that section blank. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>You will not receive credit for listing examination procedures you WOULD have done or questions you WOULD have asked had the encounter been longer. Write <strong>ONLY</strong> the information you elicited from the patient through either physical examination or history taking.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>When you hear the announcement to stop writing, put down your pen <strong>immediately</strong> or click "Submit" on the computer. Continuing to write after the announcement&#xD;
to stop will be considered misconduct. Remain seated until all examinees' patient notes have been collected.</p>&#xD;
	<h2>Other Case Formats</h2>&#xD;
	<p>The kinds of medical problems that your patients will portray are those you would commonly encounter in a clinic, doctor's office, emergency department, or hospital setting. Although there are no young children presenting as patients, there may be cases in which you encounter &#x2014; either in the examination room or via the telephone &#x2014; a parent or caregiver of a child.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>In some instances you may be instructed to perform a physical examination that relates to a specific medical condition, life circumstance, or occupation. Synthetic models, mannequins, or simulators provide an appropriate format for assessment of sensitive examination skills such as genital or rectal examination, and may be used for these cases. In such cases, specific instructions regarding the use of these devices will be provided. If you encounter any case for which you decide no physical examination is necessary, leave that section of the patient note blank.</p>&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
<h1>Testing Regulations and Rules of Conduct </h1>&#xD;
<p><strong>You cannot discuss the cases with your fellow examinees, during breaks or at any time.</strong></p>&#xD;
<p>Conversation among examinees in languages other than English about any subject is strictly prohibited at all times, including during breaks. Test center staff will be with you to monitor activity. To maintain security and quality assurance, each examination room is equipped with video cameras and microphones to record every patient encounter.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>The USMLE program retains the right to remove any examinee from the examination who appears to represent a health or safety risk to the standardized patients or staff of a clinical skills evaluation center. This includes, but is not limited to, examinees who appear ill, are persistently coughing or sneezing, have open skin lesions, or have evidence of active bleeding. Examinees who are not feeling well are encouraged to seek medical advice prior to arrival at the center and, if consistent with medical advice, should consider rescheduling the date of their examination. This can be done at the website of your registration entity.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Clinical skills evaluation center staff monitor all testing administrations for the Step 2 CS examination. You must follow instructions of test center staff throughout the examination. Failure to do so may result in a determination of irregular behavior. The <em><a href="../../../../General_Information/general_information_bulletin.html">USMLE Bulletin of Information</a></em> provides a complete description of irregular behavior and the consequences of a finding of irregular behavior in the sections titled <strong>Testing Regulations and Rules of Conduct</strong> and<strong> Irregular Behavior</strong>. You must become familiar with the <em>Bulletin of Information</em> before you take your examination.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<h2>Irregular Behavior</h2>&#xD;
<p>Irregular behavior includes any action by applicants, examinees, potential applicants, or others when solicited by an applicant and/or examinee that subverts or attempts to subvert the examination process. Specific examples of irregular behavior include, but are not limited to:</p>&#xD;
<ul><li>Seeking and/or obtaining unauthorized access to examination materials;</li> &#xD;
		<li>Providing false information or making false statements on application forms or other USMLE-related documents; </li>&#xD;
		<li>Taking an examination without being eligible for it or attempting to do so;</li> &#xD;
		<li>Impersonating an examinee or engaging someone else to take the examination for you; </li>&#xD;
		<li>Giving, receiving, or obtaining unauthorized assistance during the examination or attempting to do so; </li>&#xD;
		<li>Making notes of any kind during the examination, except on the blank paper provided to you; </li>&#xD;
		<li>Failure to adhere to any USMLE policy, procedure or rule, including instructions of the test center staff; </li>&#xD;
		<li>Disruptive or unprofessional behavior at the test center; </li>&#xD;
		<li>Interacting with any standardized patient outside of that standardized patient's given case portrayal, before, during, or after the examination; </li>&#xD;
		<li>Conversing with other Step 2 CS examinees in any language other than English at any time while at the test center; </li>&#xD;
		<li>Possessing unauthorized materials, including notes and study guides, photographic equipment, communication or recording devices, pagers, cellular phones, watches of any type, and personal digital assistants (PDAs) during the entire testing session, including during breaks; </li>&#xD;
		<li>Altering or misrepresenting examination scores; </li>&#xD;
		<li>Any unauthorized reproduction by any means, including reconstruction through memorization and/or dissemination of copyrighted examination materials and examination content (this includes the reproduction and dissemination of examination content on the Internet, email and listservs);</li> &#xD;
		<li>Providing or attempting to provide any information, including that relating to examination content, that may give or attempt to give unfair advantage to individuals who may be taking the examination; </li>&#xD;
		<li>Engaging in behaviors that could constitute a real or potential threat to a patient's safety, such as careless or dangerous actions during physical examination. </li>&#xD;
	</ul><p>Instances of possible irregular behavior are thoroughly investigated and actions may be taken under the USMLE policies and procedures on irregular behavior. </p>&#xD;
<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
<h1>Scoring the Step 2 CS Examination </h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Step 2 CS is designed to evaluate your ability to gather information that is important for a given patient presentation. During your physical examination of the standardized patient, you should attempt to elicit important positive and negative signs. Make sure you discuss with the patient your initial diagnostic impression and work-up plan. The patients may ask questions concerning their complaints. You should address each patient's concern as you would in a normal clinical setting.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>The ability to communicate effectively with patients, demonstrating appropriate interpersonal skills, is essential to safe and effective patient care.Step 2 CS&#xD;
is intended to determine whether physicians seeking&#xD;
an initial license to practice medicine in the United&#xD;
States, regardless of country of origin, can communicate&#xD;
effectively with patients. Carefully developed rating&#xD;
scales, as well as intensive training in their use,&#xD;
are used by the standardized patients to assess communication,&#xD;
interpersonal skills, and English-speaking&#xD;
skills.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p>Your ability to document in the patient note the findings from the patient encounter, diagnostic impression, and initial patient work-up will be rated by physician raters. You will be rated based upon the quality of documentation of important positive and negative findings from the history and physical examination, as well as your listed differential diagnoses and diagnostic assessment plans. As is the case with other aspects of Step 2 CS scoring, physician raters receive intensive training and monitoring to ensure consistency and fairness in rating.</p>&#xD;
	<h2>Scoring of the Step 2 Clinical Skills Subcomponents</h2>&#xD;
	<p>USMLE Step 2 CS is a pass/fail examination. Examinees are scored in three separate subcomponents: Integrated Clinical Encounter (ICE), Communication and Interpersonal Skills (CIS), and Spoken English Proficiency (SEP). Each of the three subcomponents must be passed in a single administration in order to achieve a passing performance on &#xD;
Step 2 CS. </p>&#xD;
	<p>The ICE subcomponent includes assessment of:</p>&#xD;
	<ul><li>Data gathering - patient information collected by history taking and physical examination </li>&#xD;
		<li>Documentation - completion of a patient note summarizing the findings of the patient encounter, diagnostic impression, and initial patient work-up </li>&#xD;
	</ul><p>Data gathering is scored by checklists completed by the standardized patients. The checklists are developed by committees of clinicians and medical school clinical faculty and comprise the essential history and physical examination elements for specific clinical encounters. The patient note is scored by trained physician raters. Copies of the patient note template, sample patient note styles, and software to practice typing the note are available on the USMLE website. (See also Appendices A - C.)</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<p>The CIS subcomponent includes assessment of:</p>&#xD;
	<div class="blue-bg">&#xD;
	 <strong>Questioning skills - examples include:</strong>&#xD;
          <ul><li><em>use of</em> open-ended questions, transitional statements, facilitating remarks</li>&#xD;
           <li><em>avoidance of</em> leading or multiple questions, repeat questions unless for clarification, medical terms/jargon unless immediately defined, interruptions when the patient is talking</li>&#xD;
          <li><em>accurately summarizing</em> information from the patient</li>&#xD;
		  </ul></div>&#xD;
	<div class="blue-bg">&#xD;
    <strong>Information-sharing skills - examples include:</strong>&#xD;
	<ul><li><em>acknowledging</em> patient issues/concerns and clearly responding with information</li>&#xD;
          <li><em>avoidance of</em> medical terms/jargon unless immediately defined</li>&#xD;
          <li><em>clearly providing</em> &#xD;
		  	<ul><li class="bullet">counseling when appropriate</li>&#xD;
			  <li class="bullet">closure, including statements about what happens next</li>&#xD;
		  	</ul></li>&#xD;
	</ul></div>&#xD;
	<div class="blue-bg">&#xD;
    <strong>Professional manner and rapport - examples include:</strong>&#xD;
          <ul><li><em>asking about</em>&#xD;
				<ul><li class="bullet">expectations, feelings, and concerns of the patient</li>&#xD;
					<li class="bullet">support systems and impact of illness, with attempts to explore these areas</li>&#xD;
				</ul></li>&#xD;
          <li><em>showing</em>&#xD;
				<ul><li class="bullet">consideration for patient comfort during the physical examination</li>&#xD;
					<li class="bullet">attention to cleanliness through hand washing or use of gloves</li>&#xD;
				</ul></li>	&#xD;
          <li><em>providing</em> opportunity for the patient to express feelings/concerns</li>&#xD;
          <li><em>encouraging</em> additional questions or discussion</li>&#xD;
          <li><em>making</em>&#xD;
				<ul><li class="bullet">empathetic remarks concerning patient issues/concerns</li>&#xD;
					<li class="bullet">patient feel comfortable and respected during the encounter</li>&#xD;
				</ul></li>&#xD;
			</ul></div>&#xD;
	<p>CIS performance is assessed by the standardized patients, who provide a global rating of these skills using a series of generic rating scales. The domains included in these scales are, in part, based upon the scales used in the former Clinical Skills Assessment (CSA) of the Educational Commission for Foreign Medical Graduates, with enhancements based upon national consensus statements on essential communication skills and upon review of other commonly used rating forms. </p>&#xD;
	<p>The SEP subcomponent includes assessment of:</p>&#xD;
	<ul><li>Clarity of spoken English communication within the context of the doctor-patient encounter (eg, pronunciation, word choice, and minimizing the need to repeat questions or statements) </li>&#xD;
	</ul><p>SEP performance is assessed by the standardized patients using rating scales and is based upon the frequency of pronunciation or word choice errors that affect comprehension, and the amount of listener effort required to understand the examinee's questions and responses.</p>&#xD;
	<h2>Step 2 CS Score Report Schedule</h2>&#xD;
	<p>Step 2 CS examinees are grouped into testing periods&#xD;
according to the dates on which they test. The first&#xD;
results for a given testing period will be issued on the&#xD;
first day of the corresponding reporting period, and it&#xD;
is expected that results for the vast majority of examinees&#xD;
who take the exam during the testing period will&#xD;
be reported on this date. However, it is important to&#xD;
note that there will likely be a small number of examinees&#xD;
for whom scoring and quality assurance are not&#xD;
completed by the first day of the reporting period;&#xD;
these will typically be examinees who took the exam&#xD;
in the latter part of the testing period. Results for&#xD;
these examinees will be reported each week throughout&#xD;
the reporting period, and should be reported no&#xD;
later than the last day of the score reporting period.</p>&#xD;
<p>This schedule allows USMLE staff to enhance the&#xD;
quality assurance and data collection/scoring procedures&#xD;
performed prior to score reporting. Additionally,&#xD;
it provides examinees, as well as others who rely on&#xD;
Step 2 CS results, with guidelines regarding when a&#xD;
result will be reported for a given exam date. These&#xD;
guidelines allow examinees to plan their exam registration&#xD;
and scheduling in order to have their results in&#xD;
time to meet specific deadlines, such as those related&#xD;
to graduation or participation in the National Resident&#xD;
Matching Program (NRMP), or "the Match."&#xD;
Information about  testing periods and corresponding&#xD;
reporting periods is <a href="../../step2cs_reporting.html">available</a>.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>Terms Used in the Step 2 CS Examination </h1>&#xD;
	&#xD;
	<p>Lists similar to the one below will be available on-site for reference during Step 2 CS administrations.</p>&#xD;
	<div class="smallColumnLeft">&#xD;
	<table><tr><th colspan="2">UNITS OF MEASURE</th>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>kg</td>&#xD;
			<td>kilogram</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>g</td>&#xD;
			<td>gram</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>mcg</td>&#xD;
	  <td>microgram</td>&#xD;
	  </tr><tr><td>mg</td>&#xD;
			<td>milligram</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>lbs</td>&#xD;
			<td>pounds</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>oz</td>&#xD;
			<td>ounces</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>m</td>&#xD;
			<td>meter</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>cm</td>&#xD;
			<td>centimeter</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>min</td>&#xD;
			<td>minute</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>hr</td>&#xD;
			<td>hour</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>C</td>&#xD;
			<td>Celsius</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>F</td>&#xD;
			<td>Fahrenheit</td>&#xD;
	</tr></table></div>&#xD;
	<div class="smallColumnRight">&#xD;
	<table><tr><th colspan="2">VITAL SIGNS</th>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>BP</td>&#xD;
		<td>blood pressure</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>HR</td>&#xD;
		<td>heart rate</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>R</td>&#xD;
		<td>respirations</td>&#xD;
	</tr><tr><td>T</td>&#xD;
		<td>temperature</td>&#xD;
	</tr></table></div>&#xD;
&#xD;
	&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
<h1>Common Abbreviations for the Patient Note </h1>&#xD;
&#xD;
<p><strong>Note:</strong> This is not intended to be a complete list of acceptable abbreviations, but rather represents the types of common abbreviations that may be used on the patient note. There is no need to use abbreviations on the patient note; if you are in doubt about the correct abbreviation, write it out.</p>&#xD;
&#xD;
<div class="smallColumnLeft">&#xD;
	<dl><dt><strong>yo</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>m</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>f</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>b</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>w</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>L</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>R</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>hx</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>h/o</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>c/o</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>&#xD8;</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>+</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>-</strong></dt>&#xD;
	</dl><br/><br/><dl><dt><strong>Abd</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>AIDS</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>AP</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>BUN</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>CABG</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>CBC</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>CCU</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>CHF</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dd><strong>cig</strong></dd>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>COPD</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>CPR</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>CT</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>CVA</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>CVP</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>CXR</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>DM</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>DTR</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>ECG</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>ED</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>EMT</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>ENT</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>EOM</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>ETOH</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>Ext</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>FH</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>GI</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>GU</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>HEENT</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>HIV</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>HTN</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>IM</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>IV</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>JVD</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>KUB</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>LMP</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>LP</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>MI</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>MRI</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>MVA</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>Neuro</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>NIDDM</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>NKA</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>NKDA</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dd><strong>NL</strong></dd>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>NSR</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>P</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dd><strong>PA</strong></dd>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>PERLA</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>po</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>PT</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>PTT</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>RBC</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>SH</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>TIA</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>U/A</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>URI</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dt><strong>WBC</strong></dt>&#xD;
		<dd><strong>WNL</strong></dd>&#xD;
	</dl></div>&#xD;
<div class="smallColumnRight">&#xD;
	<dl><dt>year-old</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>male</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>female</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>black</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>white</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>left</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>right</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>history</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>history of</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>complaining of</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>without or no</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>positive</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>negative</dt>&#xD;
	</dl><br/><br/><dl><dt>abdomen</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>acquired immune deficiency syndrome</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>anteroposterior</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>blood urea nitrogen</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>coronary artery bypass grafting</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>complete blood count</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>cardiac care unit</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>congestive heart failure</dt>&#xD;
		<dd>cigarettes</dd>&#xD;
		<dt>chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>cardiopulmonary resuscitation</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>computed tomography</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>cerebrovascular accident</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>central venous pressure</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>chest x-ray</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>diabetes mellitus</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>deep tendon reflexes</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>electrocardiogram</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>emergency department</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>emergency medical technician</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>ears, nose, and throat</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>extraocular muscles</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>alcohol</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>extremities</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>family history</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>gastrointestinal</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>genitourinary</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>head, eyes, ears, nose, and throat</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>human immunodeficiency virus</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>hypertension</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>intramuscularly</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>intravenously</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>jugular venous distention</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>kidney, ureter, and bladder</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>last menstrual period</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>lumbar puncture</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>myocardial infarction</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>magnetic resonance imaging</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>motor vehicle accident</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>neurologic</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>non-insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>no known allergies</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>no known drug allergy</dt>&#xD;
		<dd>normal/normal limits </dd>&#xD;
		<dt>normal sinus rhythm</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>pulse/heart rate </dt>&#xD;
		<dd>posteroanterior</dd>&#xD;
		<dt>pupils equal, react to light and accommodation</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>orally</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>prothrombin time</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>partial thromboplastin time</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>red blood cells</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>social history</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>transient ischemic attack</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>urinalysis</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>upper respiratory tract infection</dt>&#xD;
		<dt>white blood cells</dt>&#xD;
		<dd>within normal limits </dd>&#xD;
	</dl></div>&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
      <h1>Appendix A </h1>&#xD;
	  <h2>Patient Note Screen</h2>&#xD;
	<p>When  you type the patient note, you will use a program similar to the one pictured below. You can practice using the patient note software by using the program provided on the  USMLE website. The patient note screen that appears during the actual examination will have a status bar for each field, indicating how much space remains.</p>&#xD;
	<img src="/img/step2cs/PNEntry.jpg" alt="Patient Notes"/><!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
      <h1>Appendix B </h1>&#xD;
	  <h2>Sample Patient Note Styles</h2>&#xD;
	<p>Various styles of writing patient notes for the Step 2 CS examination are acceptable. Two examples of patient notes are shown; these demonstrate some of the acceptable variations in style. These examples are not meant to represent ideal or perfect patient notes, nor should they be assumed to be complete or accurate with respect to content. Both formats and styles, however, would be considered acceptable. </p>&#xD;
	<h2>Patient Note Example One</h2>&#xD;
	<p>Patient Note Example One is written primarily in a narrative style. The History section is written in complete or nearly complete sentences, and the Physical Examination section also has fairly complete phrases. Note that only four studies are ordered under the Diagnostic Workup section; this is acceptable. </p>&#xD;
&#xD;
	<p>This note uses some abbreviations not included in the list of common abbreviations that is posted at each writing station, but they are common enough to be recognizable by the practicing physicians who rate the notes. The note is written in cursive script, but it is legible. </p>&#xD;
	<h2>Patient Note Example Two </h2>&#xD;
    <p><img src="/img/step2cs/USMLEtypednote_1_640x828.jpg" width="640" height="828" alt="example 1"/></p>&#xD;
	<p>Patient Note Example Two is written in a telegraphic or "bullet" style. There are no complete sentences, although there are some complete phrases. In some parts of the History section, in particular, one or two words stand alone. The writer of this note has chosen to transcribe the patient's blood pressure from the examinee instruction sheet. You may wish to include vital signs if they are particularly relevant to the case.</p> &#xD;
&#xD;
	<p>In this note only four items are listed in both the Differential Diagnosis and in the Diagnostic Workup sections; again, this is acceptable. This sample also contains some abbreviations or symbols not included in the list of common abbreviations posted at each writing station, but, as in Example One, they are generally recognizable.</p>&#xD;
	<p><img src="/img/step2cs/USMLEtypednote_2_640x828.jpg" width="640" height="828" alt="example 2"/></p><!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
	<h1>Appendix C </h1>&#xD;
	<h2>Patient Note</h2>&#xD;
	<p>If you write the patient note by hand, you will fill out a form similar to this after each patient encounter.</p>&#xD;
	<div class="appendixA">&#xD;
		<p><strong>HISTORY:</strong> Include significant positives and negatives from history of present illness, past medical history, review of system(s), social history, and family history.</p>&#xD;
		<br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><p> <strong>PHYSICAL EXAMINATION:</strong> Indicate only pertinent positive and negative findings related to the patient's chief complaint.</p>&#xD;
		<br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><br/><div class="columnLeft">&#xD;
			<p><strong>DIFFERENTIAL DIAGNOSES: In order of likelihood </strong>(with 1 being the most likely), list up to 5 potential or possible diagnoses for this patient's presentation (in many cases, fewer than 5 diagnoses are likely):</p>&#xD;
			<dl><dt>1.</dt>&#xD;
				<dt>2.</dt>&#xD;
				<dt>3.</dt>&#xD;
				<dt>4.</dt>&#xD;
				<dt>5.</dt>&#xD;
			</dl></div>&#xD;
		<div class="columnRight">&#xD;
		<p><strong>DIAGNOSTIC WORKUP:</strong> List immediate plans (up to 5) for further diagnostic workup:</p>&#xD;
		<br/><br/><br/><br/><dl><dt>1.</dt>&#xD;
				<dt>2.</dt>&#xD;
				<dt>3.</dt>&#xD;
				<dt>4.</dt>&#xD;
				<dt>5.</dt>&#xD;
			</dl></div>&#xD;
	</div>&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div><div id="body">&#xD;
    <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main_Body" -->&#xD;
<h1>Appendix D </h1>&#xD;
<h2>Clinical Skills Evaluation Collaboration (CSEC) Center Addresses</h2>&#xD;
<br/><center><p>Travel information about each location is available at <br/><a href="../CSECAddresses.html">www.usmle.org/step2/step2CS/CSECAddresses.htm</a>.</p></center>&#xD;
<p><strong>CSEC Center - Atlanta</strong><br/>&#xD;
Two Crown Center<br/>&#xD;
1745 Phoenix Boulevard<br/>&#xD;
Suite 500, 5th Floor<br/>&#xD;
Atlanta, GA 30349</p>&#xD;
<p><strong>CSEC Center - Chicago</strong><br/>&#xD;
First Midwest Bank Building, 6th Floor<br/>&#xD;
8501 West Higgins Road, Suite 600 <br/>&#xD;
Chicago, IL 60631</p>&#xD;
<p><strong>CSEC Center - Houston</strong><br/>&#xD;
Amegy Bank Building, 7th Floor<br/>&#xD;
400 North Sam Houston Parkway<br/>&#xD;
Suite 700<br/>&#xD;
Houston, TX 77060</p>&#xD;
<p><strong>CSEC Center - Los Angeles</strong><br/>&#xD;
Pacific Corporate Towers<br/>&#xD;
100 North Sepulveda Boulevard, 13th Floor<br/>&#xD;
El Segundo, CA 90245</p>&#xD;
<p><strong>CSEC Center - Philadelphia</strong><br/>&#xD;
Science Center<br/>&#xD;
3624 Market Street, 3rd Floor<br/>&#xD;
Philadelphia, PA 19104</p>&#xD;
<p><strong>OR</strong></p>&#xD;
<p>3700 Market Street, 2nd Floor<br/>&#xD;
  Philadelphia, PA 19104&#xD;
</p>&#xD;
<!-- InstanceEndEditable -->    </div>
</div>
